<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The neck of the Quakers broken, or, cut in sunder by the two-edged sword of the spirit which is put into my mouth first, in a letter to Edward Bourne a Quaker, secondly, in answer to a letter to Samuel Hooton and W.S., thirdly, in a letter to Richard Farnsworth, Quaker, fourthly, in an answer to a printed pamphlet of the said Richard Farnsworth, entituled, Truth ascended, or, The annointed and sealed of the Lord defended, &amp;c. / written by Lodowick Muggleton ...</title>
            <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R896</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12496800</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12496800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62519</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62519)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 769:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The neck of the Quakers broken, or, cut in sunder by the two-edged sword of the spirit which is put into my mouth first, in a letter to Edward Bourne a Quaker, secondly, in answer to a letter to Samuel Hooton and W.S., thirdly, in a letter to Richard Farnsworth, Quaker, fourthly, in an answer to a printed pamphlet of the said Richard Farnsworth, entituled, Truth ascended, or, The annointed and sealed of the Lord defended, &amp;c. / written by Lodowick Muggleton ...</title>
                  <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>82 [i.e. 80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.] :</publisher>
                  <publisher>printed ... and are to be had in Great Trinity-Lane ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>It was claimed at Muggleton's trial in January 1677 that this work was actually published at London in 1676. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>R. F. --  (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</term>
               <term>Hooton, Samuel.</term>
               <term>Bourne, Edward, d. 1708.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62519:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62519:1"/>
            <p>The Neck of the QUAKERS BROKEN: OR, Cut in ſunder by the two-edged Sword of the Spirit which is put into my Mouth.
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, In a Letter to <hi>Edward Bourne</hi> a Quaker.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, In Anſwer to a Letter to <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, In a Letter to <hi>Richard Farnſworth,</hi> Quaker.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, In an Anſwer to a printed Pamphlet of the ſaid <hi>Richard Farnſworth,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Truth Aſcended:</hi> Or, <hi>The Anointed and Sealed of the Lord defended,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> one of the two Iuſt Prophets and Witneſſes unto the High and Mighty God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AMSTERDAM:</hi> Printed in the Year of our Lord God, 1663.</p>
            <p>And are to be had in <hi>Great Trinity-Lane,</hi> over againſt the Lyon and the Lamb.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:62519:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62519:2"/>
            <head>Lodowick Muggleton<hi>'s LETTER TO</hi> Edward Bourne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Saw a Letter of yours which you ſent to <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> wherein I perceive ſhe did lend you a Book of ours, of the Two Witneſſes of the Spirit, which you have peruſed, not for your good, but for your eternal hurt; for you have diſcovered in that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per what ſeed and nature you are of, which is the reprobate Angels ſeed and nature which is called in Scripture <hi>A Serpent,</hi> or <hi>Devil,</hi> of whoſe ſeed or childe you are one, which you have plainly expreſſed in your Letter, by ſpeaking evil of the things you do not know, in which Book or Books you were not worthy to look into: But many more beſides you of the Serpents brood have ſtumbled at this ſtone, even the Commiſſion of the Spirit, to their eternal condemnation, which we the Witneſſes of the Spirit have denounced upon them, which no infinite Spirit or Light of Chriſt within them ſhall take it off from them, nor deliver them in the day of trouble.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſhew in ſome particular places in your Letter wherein you have ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt, a ſin that will never be forgiven in this world, nor in the world to come. And ſo I ſhall proceed to the ſentence of eternal death upon you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you ſay that you peruſed the Book till you was weary with looking into it, for it was one of the dirtyeſt and confuſedſt piece of work that ever you ſaw.</p>
            <p>Alſo you do adviſe <hi>Dorothy Carter</hi> to conſider of it, and let the witneſs of her own conſcience anſwer whether it was given
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62519:3"/>
forth from the Spirit of Truth, or from the ſpirit of error and deceit, or not.</p>
            <p>This I would have you to know, though it be too late for your good, that it is neither the light in her, nor in you, nor no man under heaven at this day, that can, or ought to judge of the Doctrine or Declaration of a Prophet that hath a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from God, but ought rather to ſubmit and yield obedience to their Doctrine; for there is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of it: For <hi>whoſoever receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet, ſhall receive a prophets reward:</hi> which reward is no leſs then the aſſurance of eternal life. So on the contrary, he that deſpiſeth a prophet; Doctrine, deſpiſeth him that ſent him, and ſhall receive from that Prophet the ſeal in his conſcience of his eternal damnation.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that you take offence at, is that we ſay that the reprobate Angel had the womb of a woman to clothe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with fleſh alſo to bring forth Gods deſign: From which you do ask, whether that which is the Devils work can be Gods glorious deſign, ſeeing God hath manifeſted his Son to deſtroy the works of the Devil?</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That the reprobate Angel clothing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with fleſh in the womb of a woman, it was Gods deſign that the reprobate Angel ſhould do ſo for this very purpoſe, that there might be a generation of men and women of his ſeed brought forth here in this earth, in the ſtate of mortality, being horn under the Law, it being written in their ſeed and nature, and by the not fulfilling of that law which is written in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents ſeed, it is made capable to ſuffer the pains of eternal death, which is the ſecond death, and this was Gods deſign, that he might deſtroy the ſeed of the ſerpent with a ſecond death.</p>
            <p>And as for Gods deſtroying the works of the Devil, he doth deſtroy them two ways, that is, he that is God did lay down his ſpiritual and heavenly glory in the womb of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, and ſo clothing himſelf with fleſh and bone, ſo that he might be capable to ſuffer the pains of death: therefore it is ſaid in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>that this Jeſus which is called the Son of God:</hi> but in other places of Scripture he is called the <hi>Very God,</hi> as the Epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>This is the very God and Eternal Life.</hi> And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62519:3"/>
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>To us a Childe is born, to us a Son is given,</hi> attributing to that Childe Jeſus the Title of <hi>Everlaſting Father, Mighty God,</hi> and <hi>Prince of Peace.</hi> There might be more places of Scriptures named to prove this thing, as that ſaying, <hi>that the fulneſs of the God-head dwelt bodily in him:</hi> and that ſaying in the <hi>Revelation, I am Alpha and Omega, the firſt and the laſt: he that was dead, but am alive, and behold I live for evermore:</hi> And as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel by taking fleſh upon him by entring into the womb of <hi>Eve,</hi> brought ſin and death into the world unto the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo God by clothing himſelf with fleſh in the womb of a Virgin, that he might be put to death in that fleſh, and by his ſpirit quickning again in that fleſh, he will deſtroy him that had the power of death, which is the devil, and the devils works.</p>
            <p>He deſtroyed the works of the devil in the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> by their having faith in the death of God, which faith purifies the heart, and is juſtified in the ſight of God, and in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſo the works of the devil are deſtroyed in the ſeed of Faith, which is the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> by believing in the blood of God, they having their hearts ſprinkled by faith in his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> and this did God procure to his own ſeed, by clothing himſelf with fleſh. So on the contrary, he by his deſign of clothing himſelf with fleſh, hath procured the eternal deſtruction to that reprobate Angel and his ſeed, and you being one of the devils ſons, I know by your words, for by your words you ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; for you have plainly ſhewed unto me by your Letter what ſeed you are of, and who your father is, even the ſame as was <hi>Cains</hi> father, you and he have all one father, for you were begotten of that wicked one, even that reprobate Angel which God deſigned him and his ſeed unto that endleſs miſery, as is ſpoken of in that Book which you call a Confuſion and a Lie: And not onely ſo, but you have called many heavenly My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, the Bottomleſs pit of Confuſion, as that God created the perſon of the ſerpent more glorious than the reſt of the holy Angels.</p>
            <p>Alſo you would have it proved by Scripture, that God made Angels ſpiritual perſons; neither can it enter into your heart to believe that the ſerpent was made by the Wiſdom and ſecret Council of God, to bring forth his ſeed to oppoſe the Creator;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62519:4"/>
and yet you read in the Scripture, <hi>that God would put enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſeed of the ſerpent, and the ſeed of the woman.</hi> From what did this ſeed of the ſerpent come, but from that reprobate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel which is always in oppoſition unto the ſeed of the woman, which is the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> which is the ſeed of Faith, which is the ſeed of God?</p>
            <p>The knowledge of theſe two Seeds is that which can truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the true meaning of the Scriptures, and open the gates of hell, and let in all the ſeed of the ſerpent who deny a perſonal God in fleſh and bone glorified: Alſo the knowledge of the two ſeeds doth open the gate of heaven unto the ſeed of Faith, and lets them enter in to that everlaſting glory, where they ſhall ſee their God face to face to their eternal joy, becauſe God hath a body and face, and ſo ſhall every ſeed have a face of its own. And though the ſeed of the ſerpent ſhall have a face of its own, yet it ſhall never ſee the face of God, Angels, nor man, no nor their own face, to eternity: for as they lived and died in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here in this world, not knowing what the form and nature of the true God is, nor the form and nature of the right Devil; and ſo not knowing what nature and ſeed themſelves are of, they ſhall riſe again in that eternal darkneſs, never ſtirring from the place they are raiſed, to eternity.</p>
            <p>I write theſe Lines unto you <hi>Edward Bourne,</hi> knowing you to be of the ſeed of the ſerpent, and appointed to eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before you were born, though you know it not, I do know it by your ſpeaking evil of that doctrine which is declared by us the VVitneſſes of the Spirit, by calling of it Deceit, Confuſion, and Lies, with many more wicked ſpeeches againſt the pureſt Truth that ever was declared by Prophet or Apoſtle, becauſe this is the Commiſſion of the Spirit, and the laſt Witneſs of God on earth.</p>
            <p>Therefore for theſe your hard ſayings againſt the Doctrine of this Commiſsion of the Spirit, in obedience unto my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, I do pronounce you curſed and damned ſoul and body from the preſence of God, elect men and Angels, to eternity; neither ſhall that light within you, nor any God deliver you from this Curſe, but according to my word it ſhall be upon you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſhall know that God hath given power unto man to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62519:4"/>
curſe you to eternity, and that there is a Prophet of the Lord now in the Land.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Written by</hi> Lodowick Muggleton, <hi>one of the two laſt Witneſſes and Prophets unto the High and Mighty God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory.</hi>
               </signed>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Auguſt the 10. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A LETTER of</hi> Samuel Hooton <hi>and</hi> W. S. <hi>to</hi> Lodowick Muggleton.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOR ſo we can call thee, as Chriſt did <hi>Judas,</hi> and alſo the ſloathful ſervant whoſe talent was hid in the earth, who art in the higheſt ſtate of inchantment.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt ſlandered the children of the Moſt High God, thy lips hath uttered lies, thy tongue hath forged deceit, thou art a falſe witneſs, a wanderer, a vagabond from the true underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, true knowledge and councel, under whoſe tongue is the aſp and the venome, who out-ſputters it againſt the children of light, but with it thou art comprehended, and ſhall be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and the hook <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(Vah)</hi> is put into thy noſtrils, by which thou ſhalt be held, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Obed</hi>) is thy ſtate if thou canſt read it, which upon thee ſhall come, &amp; canſt thou read (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tame</hi>) thou haſt polluted thy ſelf, thou haſt defiled thy ſelf, thou haſt made thy ſelf unclean, and thou art unclean, and art in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtate of Ranters from the holy body, in the polluted body, and where ever thou haſt an entrance thou wilt defile, and thou mayeſt deceive fools and them that be void of underſtanding, but the ſound and the weighty thy ſpirit hath not, nor never had any entertainment; for thou art clothed with a Curſe and not with a Bleſsing, the fruits of which is ſputtered abroad, and the eternal Sentence of Judgement of the Lord God is ſentenced upon thee. And now to the matter of thy flanders, and ſcandals, and reproaches that thou caſts upon the Moſt High's children.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62519:5"/>Firſt, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>We (that are called Quakers) are guided and led by the Spirit of Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is falſe, for we are in the Spirit of Chriſt before Antichriſt was, and we have it, and are Chriſts, and ſo thy ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders doth not touch us, but is thy own, who ſpeaks of thy ſelf, and beareth witneſs of thy ſelf: but our witneſs is in Heaven which beareth witneſs of us, and witneſſeth to us, which thou haſt manifeſted thou knoweſt not, who judges with evil thoughts, and is in that judgement which is to be reproved, for we have Judgement to ſentence and judge ſuch ſpirits perpetually.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>We are the worſt of all, and the moſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all in point of doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is falſe again, and from ſlanderous lips: our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is Chriſts and the Apoſtles, and we that doth his will do know his Doctrine, and we are in the power of God that was before Sects was, and thou art the man that wanders up and down to make Sects, whoſe mouth is filled with curſing, and ſoweth it, ſo thou ſhalt reap of the ſame, which will enter into thy bowels, who art the Antichriſt out of Chriſts doctrine and the Apoſtles, and an enemy to it, which ſaith, <hi>bleſs and curſe not;</hi> therefore thou art one of the curſed children the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, who ſpeaks forth the high ſwelling words of vanity to the alluring of the luſts of the fleſh, and ſo to catch people with thy bait, but thy damnation and judgement lingreth not, nor ſlumbreth not. Remember thou waſt told this in thy life time.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>We deny both the Father and the Son to be a perſon in the form of a man, and that we deny the ſame fleſh and bone of Jeſus which ſuffered death, was layed in the grave, which roſe again, which was ſeen afterwards by his Apoſtles and others, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended up into heaven in that ſame fleſh and bone, which he ſuffered death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this we charge thee, and command thee to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the man, and the place of his abode that denied this, and is a <hi>Quaker.</hi> Secondly, thy charge is utterly falſe, and lies, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as to us, and the Lord will judge thee for ſowing ſuch lies abroad; for we own Chriſt, and none of us denies him that was propheſied of, ſeen by the Prophets and holy men of God, came according to the Prophecy, and was born of a Virgin according
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62519:5"/>
to the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and ſuffered death, and roſe again according to Scriptures, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who ſhall judge the world in righteouſneſs, whom God hath ordained: and we own that according to the fleſh he was of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the ſame that ſuffered, roſe, and aſcended into heaven, and remains in the heavens until the reſtitution of all things, and we ſit in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the expreſs image and ſubſtance of his Fathers perſon; and we own the Holy Ghoſt, and we own the Father, and knows them: And as touching Chriſts fleſh, we are bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, and we have the minde of Chriſt, and ſo thou lyer, let thy mouth be ſtopt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>If we ſhould own Chriſt to be a perſon, then that light of Chriſt which we ſo much talk of, would vaniſh like ſmoke, and come to nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this we anſwer, That thou haſt manifeſted thy darkneſs and ignorance, not knowing Chriſt, not knowing the Holy Ghoſt, not knowing the Father, not knowing Chriſts fleſh, his blood and bone, nor Chriſt and the Apoſtles doctrine, nor the Law; for firſt, <hi>The Law is light,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the law is in the heart, and with the light they ſaw Chriſt, yea his fleſh. Secondly, <hi>John</hi> he bare witneſs to the Light that enlighteneth every man that comes into the world, which is Chriſt: And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Light:</hi> and, <hi>believe in the light while ye have the light, that ye may be children:</hi> ſo there is no becoming children but by the light of Chriſt. And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs hath ſhined in our hearts, to give us the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and that was the treaſure in earthen veſſels. So firſt thou art ignorant of this treaſure, and both thee and thy doctrine, and thy principle flies away like that ſmoke thou ſpeaks of, and the light remains which is thy condemnation, the witneſs in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall anſwer it, which thou in thy uncleanneſs haſt long rebelled againſt. Secondly, thou that ſo rebels againſt the light of Chriſt we ſpeak of, knows not Chriſt his fleſh nor bone, nor the Father, nor the Holy Ghoſt. As firſt thus: the light that ſhines in the heart gives the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt, and ſo without this light they have no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him: and this we ſay to thee, and all upon the earth,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62519:6"/>
that none knows the Father, none knows the Son, none knows the Holy Ghoſt, none knows the Fleſh and Blood and Bone of Chriſt, but by the light of Chriſt, for that reveals him, and not Fleſh and Blood, for thou art like to the Jews who ſtop'd their Ears, and cloſed their Eyes to that of God within them, and therefore heard not, ſaw not, ſo was not converted; and ſuch profeſſed a Chriſt was to come, but perſecuted him when he was come, as thou doeſt now where he is made manifeſt in his light.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>That we will have no perſon at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is falſe, though thou haſt layed it down general; for Chriſt is the expreſs Image of the Fathers perſon we ſay, as in Hebrews: But thou art the man who wilt have no perſon at all that denies the light, for they that was in darkneſs could not ſee God nor Chriſt, nor the Holy Ghoſt, that hated the light, and the Apoſtle, ſaid he, in the perſon of Chriſt, which many doth witneſs now, Glory to the Lord for ever: for if thou doeſt profeſs them in thy words, yet again in thy words, thou that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the light, denies them, and ſo <hi>Babylon,</hi> and blaſphemouſly terms it to ſmoak, and for thy work the Lord will reward thee.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>A great part of us are of thoſe wicked Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that hath been given over to blood-ſhed with a ſword of Steel, or elſe to all manner of luſts of the Fleſh, and now thou ſayeſt we think by a more preciſe and exactneſs of Life to recover our peace with God, and yet deny the very perſon of God without us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Here again thou adds lie unto lie, but who is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is known by us the children of the Moſt High, and what doth the Devil rage in thee, becauſe ſome that hath been Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and uſed outward weapons formerly, now they are turned from theſe things to God and Chriſt, the expreſs Image of the Fathers perſon, and comes to live in Chriſt and ſerve him in a new life, therefore doeſt thou rage? they do not own their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer principles that comes amongſt us, but doth judge them, and deny them, and all the luſts of the fleſh, and doth their exactneſs of life and good converſation judge thine, that makes thee ſo fret and chaſe thy ſelf, and ſcoff, and calls it preciſe? and to this thou addes a lie, and ſaith we deny the very perſon of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us: but to this we ſay, God fills Heaven and Earth, and Chriſt the expreſs Image of the Fathers perſon, is manifeſt within us,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62519:6"/>
and thou who railes at this, doth manifeſt thy ſelf a reprobate, one in whom God and Chriſt is not, and an Antichriſt, and a falſe witneſs, and a lying ſpirit; for Chriſt ſaith he would dwell in the Saints, and God would dwell in them, and walk in them: and hath the devil made thee ſo blind and ignorant of the letter of the Scripture, who art given up to believe lies, and who makes lies thy refuge, and haſt thou no other refuge but lies, who by this manifeſts thy ſelf to all ſober people what thou art, and from whence thou comes, and is not repentance hid from thy eyes, it is manifeſt by thy ſpirit, yet we muſt ſay this to thee, thou art in the unclean fleſh, and hath an unclean body, thy fleſh burns with thy heat of thy luſts, and therefore thou haſt uttered forth thy ruine; nevertheleſs here is ſome queries for thee to anſwer in writing, elſe for ever ſtop thy mouth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is there any ſuch thing as ſin, and what is ſin in it ſelf, and whether thou canſt act any ſin, and expreſs what is a ſin to thee?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If thou doeſt acknowledge ſinne, then ſhall a man while he is upon Earth be made free from ſinne, and come into the ſtate that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> was in before they fell, while they be upon the earth, and come to Chriſt, a ſtate that ſhall never fall while he be upon earth?</p>
            <p n="3">3. For what end did Chriſt come, doth Chriſt enlighten every man that comes into the world with a ſaving light, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning light, yea or nay? Is there any true Prophecy, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Revelations or Witneſs ſeen or known, but by the light of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="4">4. What is the Soul, is it mortal or immortal? What is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and where is it ſeated in man? What are the Angels, and the worſhippers of Angels? What is the worſhip of the Beaſt and the Dragon? And what is the Whore that ſits upon the Beaſt, which all nations drink her Cup, and what is her Cup?</p>
            <p n="5">5. What is the woman that fled into the Wilderneſs? And what is the Wilderneſs? And what are the times, and time, and half a time that ſhe was to be fed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e? And what was the number of the Beaſt, which is the number of a man, and what is the number of a man?</p>
            <p n="6">6. What is the Serpent? And what is the Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? And what is the Tree of Life? And what is the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62519:7"/>
Sword? And what is the body of Death? And the body of Sin, is it a mans outward body yea, or nay?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Shall a man be made free from Sin and Death whileſt he be upon earth, and be made perfect?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Dare thou ſay that thou haſt the ſame Spirit and Power as Chriſt and the Apoſtles had?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Haſt thou heard the voice of God and Chriſt immediately from Heaven? Haſt thou ſeen the ſhape of God?</p>
            <p n="10">10. What is the firſt principle of the pure Religion? And what is that which leads to Repentance? And what is that which gives the knowledge of God, and of Chriſt? And whether it be within man, or without man?</p>
            <p n="11">11. What, and where is the Church of Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="12">12. Doeſt thou ſin, or canſt thou ſin? Or haſt thou any guilt for ſin?</p>
            <p n="13">13. Hath every man the Spirit of God?</p>
            <p n="14">14. What is the honor that is from above? And what is the honor that is from below?</p>
            <p n="15">15. Doeſt not thou continue in the higheſt ſtrain of Ranters? Seeing thy mouth is full of curſing, and yet thou art finding fault with thoſe that be changed from it?</p>
            <p n="16">16. What is Evil? And what is Good? And what is Light? And what is Darkneſs? And how doeſt thou know them, and diſtinguiſh them in thy ſelf? And if thou can diſtinguiſh the one from the other, then what is it to be baptized for the dead? (mark) we ask thee what this baptiſm is for the dead, and what is the dead?</p>
            <p n="17">17. What is it that leads nature out of its courſe? And what is it that defaces the glory of the firſt body? And what is the glory of the firſt body, and what is it that leads nature in its courſe? And where is it?</p>
            <p n="18">18. What is Self-righteouſneſs and its ground? And what is the Goſpel? And what is Election? And what reprobation? And what is <hi>Cains</hi> mark?</p>
            <p>Anſwer theſe things in Writing, and ſend them to <hi>Thomas Hyfield</hi> at <hi>Notingham.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62519:7"/>
            <head>Lodowick Muggleton's <hi>Anſwer to</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Hooton <hi>and</hi> VV. S.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received a paper from you two, being Quakers, wherein I finde your Spirits much moved to wrath and railing, becauſe I have told the truth to one <hi>John Levens,</hi> formerly a Sword-man in the Army, but now turned Quaker. In a Letter to him it doth concern all the Quakers all the world over, and through ſome paſſages in that Letter you have been moved by that light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, to ſend a long railing Letter unto me, with ſome Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Scripture-texts for me to anſwer; which railing Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of yours is ſo much, and your queſtions ſo many, that it would take up a volumn to anſwer.</p>
            <p>Yet nevertheleſs becauſe you are not under the ſentence of this Commiſſion already, and for the further information of other Quakers that are not under it: And for others that ſhall come to hear or ſee this Anſwer, I ſhall trouble my ſelf ſo far as to give anſwer both to the railing part of your Letter, and (if your Queries be worth the anſwering, which is not already anſwered in ſome of our writings) I ſhall ſay ſomething to them, for ſome of thoſe Scripture texts which you quote, is not worth the anſwering: And thoſe that are of moſt concernment are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, and unfolded very plainly in that Treatiſe of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the</hi> 11 <hi>Chapter of the Revelation of St. John,</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>Concerning the Tree of Life. The Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil. Of the Serpent. Of the Woman that fled into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. What that Wilderneſs is. What the time and times, and half a time is. What the Dragon is. What the Beaſt out of the Bottomleſs-pit is. What the State of</hi> Adam <hi>was in his Creation, with the Perſon and Nature of Angels, and the Immortality of the Soul,</hi> with many other deeper ſecrets then thoſe Texts of Scripture which you mention, doth or can bear; which Books that are written by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, ſuch Devils as you are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to look into.</p>
            <p>But to give anſwer to the railing part of your Paper, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62519:8"/>
hath very little elſe in it, and if there be any thing in the Queries worth the Anſwering, which is not anſwered already in ſome of our writings I ſhall do it, not rendering railing for railing, but I ſhall ſpeak what I certainly know concerning you two, and the Miniſtry of the Quakers, and all thoſe that believe them, which continue in that Faith after they have heard of this Commiſſion of the Spirit. I know what I ſpeak to be truth, as with relation to your Principles, and to your Eternal eſtate.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The firſt part of your Paper hath little in it but rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt me onely, where you ſay, <hi>that I am in the higheſt ſtate of inchauntment, in that I have ſlandered the Children of the moſt High God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I declare as I am a Prophet and Meſſenger of the true God, that the people called Quakers are not the Children of the Moſt High God, but for the generality of them, they are the children of the devil, and are the very ſeed of the devil, and were begotten by him, and I (as I am an Ambaſſador ordained of God by voice of words) can as truly ſay that they are of the ſeed of the Serpent, and ſo the Children of the Devil, as Chriſt did to the Jews, when he ſaid, that they were Serpents, yea Devils, and the Devil was their Father, ſo can I ſay by you Quakers, and many thouſands more aſwell as you, that you are the Children of the Devil, that were begotten by him, and not begotten by <hi>Adam,</hi> who never came through the loins of <hi>Adam,</hi> though they came through the womb of <hi>Eve:</hi> For this I know, that <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt-born of the Devil, and <hi>Adam</hi> had no part in the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him. And from this <hi>Cain</hi> came thoſe Jews that Chriſt called Serpents and Devils.</p>
            <p>And the Quakers people which you call the Children of the Moſt High God, are the Children of <hi>Cain,</hi> who was that Angel or Serpent that beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> which became fleſh, blood and bone, and ſo begat millions of men and women which are his Children, whereof moſt of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are: Therefore do not you ſay that I ſlander them in ſaying that they are led by the ſpirit of Anti-chriſt, and that they are the worſt of all in point of doctrine, though the beſt of all in practice of Life. For what I have ſaid of them will prove no ſlander nor ill report, but truth is ſelf;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62519:8"/>
Neither can any <hi>Quakers</hi> principles comprehend me, nor the Doctrine declared by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And as for that high inchantment, which you ſay I am in, and thoſe you call fools which believe it, ſhall finde it the power of God unto Salvation. But on the contrary you that deſpiſe it, ſhall finde it the power of God to your eternal condemnation; which many of the Speakers of the Quakers, and other opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, with many hundreds of private perſons beſides, ſhall not deliver themſelves from the Sentence, which we the Witneſſes of the Spirit have declared through a true diſcerning, which you call Enchantment; But it is the Commiſſion and power of God which ſhall war with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and all other opinions in the world; becauſe it is the two-edged Sword of the Spirit which is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t into our mouths. And this which we have ſaid againſt you <hi>Quakers,</hi> will be no ſlander or reproach, but as true as any word that ever was ſpoken by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets and Apoſtles, or Chriſt himſelf; for we are the Witneſſes of the Spirit, which is the Spirit of Truth which hath made us judge of the world in ſpiritual matters, concerning the Eternal eſtate of Mankind: And what perſon ſoever we determine judgement upon, it is ſo, and there is no revoking of it.</p>
            <p>You have written that I ſay, you that are called <hi>Quakers</hi> are guided and lead by the Spirit of Anti-chriſt.</p>
            <p>This is as true a ſaying as ever was ſpoken by Prophet of Apoſtle, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are lead and guided by the ſpirit of Anti-chriſt, for they are not in Chriſt, neither is Chriſt in them, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay they, we are in the Spirit of Chriſt before Antichriſt was.</p>
            <p>This lie exceedeth other lies, for Anti-chriſt hath been in the world ever ſince <hi>Cain</hi> was born, of whoſe ſeed and nature they are. And Chriſt came into the world when <hi>Abel</hi> was born, then was the Seed and Nature of <hi>Adam,</hi> which is the Spirit of Faith, which is called by the Apoſtle, the Spirit of Chriſt, and who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is partaker of the Seed of <hi>Adam,</hi> may be ſaid to have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt in them, and their ſpirits to be in him, that is, Chriſt dwells in their hearts by Faith.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, the <hi>Quakers</hi> being the ſeed and nature of the loſt Angel, whoſe nature was before his fall pure reaſon, and <hi>Cain</hi> being the firſt born of the Devil, the fulneſs of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62519:9"/>
Angels Godhead dwelt bodily in him, and <hi>Cain</hi> having copulation with the female Sex, millions of men and women have been brought forth of his ſeed which is reaſon fallen, and this ſeed of reaſon in <hi>Cain</hi> and his ſeed, is that ſpirit of Anti-chriſt, and this began to act it ſelf forth when <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> began for to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, and ever ſince the ſpirit of Anti-chriſt hath remained in its ſeed, which brake forth in this later age, in a more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent manner in one particular perſon, namely <hi>John Robins,</hi> that ſeemingly carried a more pure God-like power, then any other Anti-chriſt which went before him. And the <hi>Quakers</hi> have the very influence of <hi>John Robins</hi> his ſpiritual witchcraft-power up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; And ſo indeed it may be truely ſaid that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are lead and guided by the ſpirit of Anti-chriſt, and ſo their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is in him, and his ſpirit in them, ſo that they cannot be in Chriſt nor Chriſt in them, for they are not of that ſeed that ſhould have made them the children of the Moſt High God, though I know they cannot help it, yet it is ſo decreed by the Creator, and he hath been pleaſed to make it known unto me; and though you ſay I bear witneſs of my ſelf, yet is my witneſs and judgement in theſe things, true.</p>
            <p>Whereas you rail in that I ſaid the <hi>Quakers</hi> are the worſt of all, and moſt curſedſt of all in point of Doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Anſwer.</hi> As to the ſlander and lies you ſpeak of, I ſhall let them paſs, for I have ſpake enough of them before; but as for that ſaying of mine aforeſaid, <hi>That the people called Quakers are the worſt of all, and the moſt curſedſt of all in point of Doctrine,</hi> That is as pure a truth as ever was ſpoken with tongue, neither do you know the doctrine of Chriſt, neither can you do his will.</p>
            <p>How can you know the Doctrine of Chriſt? When as your Chriſt hath never a body, for you have got your Chriſt all within you, as I ſhall make more appear hereafter.</p>
            <p>And as for my wandering up and down to make Sects, it is thoſe of the <hi>Quakers</hi> that wander up and down. As thoſe that went to <hi>New-England,</hi> and <hi>John Parrot</hi> unto <hi>Rome,</hi> to get the Pope and his Biſhops to be Diſciples of Chriſt, and there to be puniſhed in his body, and when he came home again to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to eternity by me for his pains, becauſe he went by the light within him, and was not ſent by voice of God without him.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62519:9"/>
Therefore eternal damnation will be his reward for going without a Commiſſion from God, and ſo will all the Miniſters of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and all other Miniſters too for going Embaſſadors for Chriſt when as he ſent them not.</p>
            <p>Though they preach from the letter of the Scriptures, or from a light within them, though the Devils be caſt out, and much good done thereby, yet it will be but as a work of iniquity, becauſe they went before they were ſent.</p>
            <p>O how willingly is Reaſon the devil to be an Embaſſador for Chriſt, when a Chriſt will not accept of him, therefore reaſon the devil goes of himſelf thinking to have a reward in heaven, for he will ſay, Lord have not we preached in thy Name, and prayed in thy Name, and caſt out devils in thy Name? and the Lord will ſay, depart from me you workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>So that what man ſoever that preacheth or pretendeth to be a Miniſter, an Embaſſador of Chriſt without a Commiſſion from him, it will be charged upon him as a work of iniquity.</p>
            <p>Indeed there are too many Meſſengers and Miniſters of Chriſt to be true, for indeed the world can hardly bear with one true Meſſenger at a time, this I can truly ſpeak by experience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am the laſt man that God will give a Commiſſion unto, until time be no more; yet never was there any Prophet, or Apoſtle, or Meſſenger of Chriſt, but they have travelled up and down more then ever I did, almoſt theſe eleven years, ſo that I have not travelled up and down as the <hi>Quakers</hi> have, for to get either wiſe or fools to believe me: Yet this Commiſſion hath gone through more parts of the world then any <hi>Quakers</hi> ever did, but that is a thing I do not much matter.</p>
            <p>You <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay that my mouth is full of curſing, and that I ſhall reap of the ſame: likewiſe you ſay that I am out of Chriſts and the Apoſtles Doctrine, that ſaid bleſs and curſe not, with many other ſayings, which will be too tedious for me to write.</p>
            <p>As for my mouth being full of curſing, that is my Commiſſion: neither do I curſe any but Devils which are appointed for it of God, and there is never a one that I have curſed that ſhall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape that curſe which I have denounced upon them, neither will any God deliver them from it, for I do curſe none but the ſeed of the Serpent, who had his curſe denounced upon him and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62519:10"/>
his ſeed at the beginning by God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now in this laſt age God hath given me power, and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to determine and give judgement upon men and women, according as I do diſcern by their words, and I thereby alſo know what nature and ſeed they are of, and accordingly I give judgement upon them, for I do go by as certain a rule as the Judges of the Land do, when they give true Judgement accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law. For God hath ordained me the chief Judge in the world at this day to give ſentence upon men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens ſpiritual and eternal eſtate what will become of them after death.</p>
            <p>Full of this curſing I confeſs my mouth is, and I do rejoyce in it too, I know that God is well pleaſed in the damnation of thoſe that I have curſed, and I am wonderous well ſatisfied in giving judgement upon them, according to the tenor of my Commiſſion: and this is that which you call ſwelling words.</p>
            <p>You would have called the Prophet <hi>Eliahs</hi> words ſwelling words, if you had been of thoſe four hundred prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> which he commanded to be ſlain by the power of his word; which power of the Commiſſion of the Spirit, is of a more high nature then that of <hi>Eliah's</hi> was; for his was but the ſentence of death natural, but this is the ſentence of death eternal; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not immediately executed as his was, you think that there is nothing in it, but it will be found ſuddenly enough both to you and to many that are entred into the ſecond death alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: for there is no time to the dead, but after death to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which judgement they have in themſelves, which is the remembrance of that ſentence, that we who are Witneſſes of the Spirit, did paſs upon them in this life, for they ſhall never ſee any other God or Judge, but that ſentence that we have paſſed upon them.</p>
            <p>You are much miſtaken if you think to deal with a Prophet, that hath a Commiſſion from God, as you deal with the Prieſts of the nation: Becauſe you <hi>Quakers</hi> have baffled the Prieſts of the nation by that light within you, becauſe you are faln to a more preciſe exactneſs of life then they, though your doctrine is worſe then theirs, you muſt not think to do ſo by a Commiſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62519:10"/>This Commiſſion of the Spirit ſhall break the Neck of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as it hath done divers others: for this take you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that after the Sentence is paſſed upon the Speakers of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> they ſhall never grow more to any great experience, neither ſhall they have thoſe Viſions, Apparitions and Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from that light within them as they had before, but ſhall rather wither.</p>
            <p>This experience hath been known by <hi>Quakers</hi> and others, as <hi>John Robins, John Taney, John Harwood, Fox</hi> the elder, <hi>Fox</hi> the younger, <hi>Edward Burrowes, Francis Mowgil,</hi> with many others, with hundreds of all Sects beſides, which ſhall not eſcape what hath been decla ed by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>As for that ſaying which you quote out of Chriſts words to his diſciples before they had their Commiſſion, where he ſaid unto them, <hi>Bleſs, and curſe not,</hi> that concerns not me, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man in the world at this day. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had power both to bleſs and curſe after they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their Commiſsion, which was after Chriſts Aſcenſion, as you may read in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> then was that ſaying of Chriſt fulfilled which he had ſaid unto <hi>Peter, I have given thee the Keys of Heaven and of Hell, that what thou bindeſt upon earth ſhall be bound in heaven, and what thou looſeſt on earth ſhall be looſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Or thus: <hi>What ſins thou remitteſt ſhall be remitted, and whoſe ſins thou retains ſhall be retained;</hi> That is, thou ſhalt have power to give Sentence of Bleſſedneſs to thoſe that believe thee, and Sentence of Curſedneſs to thoſe that deſpiſe thy Declaration.</p>
            <p>This was the remitting of ſins, and the retaining of them, ſo that <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles were not tyed after they had received their Commiſsion to thoſe words of Chriſt which he ſpake unto them when they were private Believers. Neither am I tyed to thoſe words of Chriſt which he ſpake unto his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples at that time; for he hath given me power and authority to be Judge of the Scriptures, he hath given me underſtanding of his minde in the Scriptures above all men in the world at this day; nay, if I ſhould ſay than all the men ſince the beginning of the world, I ſhould not lye: for I being the choſen Witneſs of the Spirit, and the laſt man that ſhall ever ſpeak to this bloody, unbelieving world by Commiſsion from God; for he will never
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62519:11"/>
chuſe any more after me ſo long as the World endureth.</p>
            <p>Neither doth any man know the Scriptures, neither can any man interpret the Scriptures truly but my ſelf; for God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Scriptures into my hands, even as he gave the Prieſts Office into the hands of <hi>Aaron;</hi> none ought to officiate the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Prieſthood but <hi>Aaron,</hi> and thoſe that were appointed by <hi>Moſes</hi> and him: So it is now, none ought to officiate the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Miniſter, Meſſenger, or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, but thoſe that are approved of by <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf. For by reading the letter of the Scriptures, or the light within a man, is not ſufficient to make a man a Miniſter, Meſſenger, or Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of Chriſt; therefore thoſe words which Chriſt ſaid to his diſciples, <hi>bleſs and curſe not,</hi> is nothing to me; for he hath given me power ſince that to the contrary.</p>
            <p>He hath put the Two-edged Sword of his Spirit into my mouth, that whoſoever I pronounce curſed through my mouth, is curſed to eternity: And my power is as great, and rather greater than the Apoſtles was that you ſpeak of, which is called a curſed childe. The Apoſtles curſe was but a weak curſe to that power which God hath given to me; For the Apoſtle ſaith, if an Angel from heaven ſhould preach any other Doctrine than what he and the reſt of the Apoſtles had taught, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, I do not onely ſay, let him be accurſed: but if an Angel from heaven ſhould come and ſay I have ſpoken falſe, or lyed in the Doctrine that we have declared, and in thoſe things which I have ſaid concerning the <hi>Quakers,</hi> I have power not onely to ſay, let him be curſed, but to curſe Angel or man to eternity.</p>
            <p>As for your judgement from the letter of the Scriptures, or from the light within you, it is not worth a ſtraw: but the curſe that I pronounce upon men and women, it is not from the light of the Scriptures, nor from the light within me, but from the power and authourity of a Commiſsion received from a God without me, which ſpake by voice of words to the hearing of the ear, and this is that curſe that ſhall remain, and be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by all thoſe <hi>Quakers</hi> and others that are under it, both in this life and to eternity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, I did ſay truely in that I ſaid you deny both the Father and the Son to be a Perſon in the form of a man; and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62519:11"/>
that you deny the ſame fleſh and bone of Jeſus which ſuffered death, was laid in the grave, which roſe again, which was ſeen afterwards by his Apoſtles and others, which aſcended up into heaven in that ſame fleſh and bone that he ſuffered death in.</p>
            <p>In your Anſwer to this above-mentioned, you charge me to mention the man, and the place of his abode that denied this, and is a Quaker.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other words in this Letter of yours that is to be minded, and it is this where you ſay <hi>Chriſt Jeſus is the expreſs image and ſubſtance of the Fathers perſon, and you own the Holy Ghoſt, and you own the Father, and know them; And as touching Chriſts fleſh, you are bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, and you have the minde of Chriſt, and ſo you call me a Lyer, and ſay, let my mouth be ſtopt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſame is riddle me, riddle me, what's this? What a fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e diſtinction have you given of the Trinity, and wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſolid Arguments do you think that you have given to prove me a liar in what I have ſaid?</p>
            <p>Firſt, according to your charge, I ſhall tell you both the place and ſome of the perſons which did deny this. The place where this was denied was in <hi>Eaſtcheap,</hi> at a Butchers houſe, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who did deny thoſe things aforeſaid, one was the Butcher himſelf, I think his name was <hi>Richard Whitpan,</hi> or ſuch a like name, the <hi>Quakers Downfal</hi> doth name it right: another of them was <hi>Fox</hi> the younger, which is now both dead and damned to eternity: another of them was <hi>John Harwood,</hi> as for the other two I do n t remember their names, but one of them was a great lubberdly fellow, perhaps you may know him better than I; theſe five did all of them deny that fleſh and bone, or body of Chriſt wherein he ſuffered death, which ſame body is now living which they did deny; for which the juſt Sentence of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is paſſed upon them, as is publick in the <hi>Quakers Downfal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, it was not onely theſe five Quakers that did deny theſe things aforeſaid, but all the Quakers that ever I talked with, both men and women have done the ſame. And I know, that if I ſhould but diſcourſe with you, I ſhould finde you to do the like, for it doth not ſtand with a right Quakers principle to believe that the ſame fleſh and bone of Chriſt which ſuffered death, was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62519:12"/>
laid in the grave, roſe again, and is now living in heaven in that ſame body, neither can that body be in heaven without the ſoul or ſpirit, for where his body is, there is his ſpirit alſo, for they both lived together, they both ſuffered death together, they both roſe again together, and are both in heaven together; if ſo, how is it poſſible that the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſhould get Chriſt within them?</p>
            <p>For if Chriſt be a diſtinct perſon of himſelf, of ſubſtance fleſh and bone, though a ſpiritual body now in heaven, how comes Chriſt to get his ſpiritual body into every <hi>Quakers</hi> body, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans body elſe? For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>that the heavens ſhall contain him until the reſtitution of all things,</hi> meaning that body of fleſh and bone: ſo that the perſon of Chriſt or his Eſſence, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in this world at all, much leſs in the <hi>Quakers</hi> bodies; nay, he is not in mine, though he hath choſen me to be his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to declare what he is in his form and nature, as hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly declared in our Writings.</p>
            <p>Therefore do not you ſay that it is a ſlander and a lye for me to ſay, that you are the very abſolute ſpirit of Antichriſt, that doth deny both the Father and the Son; for though you talk of a Chriſt, and of his being the expreſs Image of his Fathers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and of a Holy Ghoſt, becauſe you read of ſuch things in Scripture, which were other mens words, ſo you reading of them, have jumbled the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt together, and ſo in ſtead of one perſon, you have gotten three perſons, and yet never a perſon. For I am ſure when I talkt with <hi>John Perrot</hi> about God, he could finde never a perſon, but an infinite Spirit without a body or perſon at all.</p>
            <p>All the <hi>Quakers</hi> that ever I have had to do withal (which have been a great many) I could never finde any <hi>Quaker</hi> to own God to be a perſon in the form of a man, but an infinite Spirit that fills heaven and earth, and all places, and all things, and ſo doth the Pope and all other Opinions that are, which doth ſhew the darkneſs of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the Pope, and all others: For if God be a perſon in the form of a man, as I am ſure he is (for I do acknowledge no other God but the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who is a diſtinct body of fleſh and bone of his own,) how then can he fill heaven and earth with his preſence, and get into the <hi>Quakers</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62519:12"/>
bodies, and all other peoples bodies too, and yet he is in heaven above the ſtars, which heaven muſt retain him until the laſt day?</p>
            <p>From this body of Chriſt which is the onely God, have I pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over all other gods or infinite ſpirits whatſoever. I could ſhew in what ſenſe it may be ſaid that God fills heaven and earth, but it would be too large to unfold, beſides it is declared already in our Writings.</p>
            <p>There is one blaſphemous ſaying of yours, through your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Scriptures, in this Letter of yours. You ſay that you do own Chriſt, according to the fleſh he was of <hi>Abraham;</hi> Which is blaſphemy to ſay it, being quite contrary to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; for thoſe Jews that perſecuted Chriſt were, according to the fleſh, the children of <hi>Abraham;</hi> therefore it was they ſaid, <hi>We have</hi> Abraham <hi>for our father, and never were in bondage to any;</hi> for indeed all thoſe that are the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh, are the children of the devil, or of the ſerpent: but all thoſe that are the children of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> or the children of the Promiſe, which is the ſeed of Faith, which are the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the Spirit, and ſo according to the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of which Chriſt came, and ſo the Seed of Faith may ſay truly they are bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, becauſe the ſeed or ſpirit of Faith which <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful had in him, liveth in our fleſh and bone, and we may be ſaid indeed to be bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, and ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Brethren, becauſe we are born not of the will of man, nor of the fleſh, but of water and of the Spirit; which Spirit doth lye ſecretly hid in the water, is the motions of peace that doth ariſe from the ſeed which is called the Spirit.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, the <hi>Quakers</hi> Chriſt is according to the fleſh of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo indeed they are bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh; for indeed they know no other Chriſt but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, that is, according to the ſeed of Reaſon. For in Scripture the ſeed of Reaſon is called the Fleſh from whence the motions of ſin doth ariſe, which are called the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the fleſh, which I have largely unfolded in <hi>The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Chapter of the Revelations,</hi> for the Scripture taketh no notice of the outward bodily fleſh, but as the two ſeeds doth operate and work in man. Reaſon is called the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62519:13"/>
Faith is called the <hi>Spirit,</hi> wherefore it is ſaid, <hi>Let Chriſt dwell in your hearts by faith.</hi> And ſo every one that doth truly believe in that fleſh and bone of Chriſt to be now living, doth eat his fleſh, and ſo Chriſt dwells in his heart by faith, and not in his perſon and eſſence, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> do vainly imagine.</p>
            <p>For they make no diſtinction between the perſon and eſſence of Chriſt, and the light of Chriſt, which light of Chriſt is one thing, and his perſon another, as the body of the Sun is one thing, and the light that ſhines from it is another, and ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh, that is, according to the ſeed of Reaſon, the <hi>Quakers</hi> are bone of his bone, and fleſh, of his fleſh: And they being the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh, as their imaginary Chriſt is; for all <hi>Abrahams</hi> children according to the fleſh, are the children of <hi>Cain,</hi> who is the father of moſt part of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and in this ſenſe they may ſay that they have the minde of Chriſt in them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You ſay I write, if you ſhould own Chriſt to be a perſon, then that light of Chriſt you ſo much talk of, would vaniſh like ſmoke and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>In your Anſwer to this, you upbraid me with my ignorance and darkneſs, as not knowing Chriſt, nor the Holy Ghoſt, nor the Father, nor Chriſts nor the Apoſtles doctrine; and for which purpoſe you quote <hi>Solomons</hi> Writings which is no Scripture, with ſome Scriptures to ſhew my ignorance, and that my Doctrine ſhould flie away like ſmoke, as I ſaid by yours, with many more ſayings that would be too tedious to write.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If I were as ignorant and as dark in the knowledge of Chriſt, and of the Holy Ghoſt, and of the Father, and of the Apoſtles doctrine as you are, it would be no matter if my tongue ſhould cleave to the roof of my mouth: for your ignorance and darkneſs is plainly diſcovered, in that you quote <hi>Solomon</hi> to prove your Scripture, light and knowledge of Chriſt, that which is no Scripture no more than the Apocrypha is, but I perceive it is as good Scripture to you as any; for you are but like a Parrot that ſpeaks other mens words, for it is nothing to you what Chriſt or the Apoſtles ſaid at that time.</p>
            <p>You ought to have heard what the Commiſſion of the Spirit ſaith now, in theſe laſt dayes; for none can interpret Scripture
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62519:13"/>
truly but my ſelf, neither doth any man in the world truly know Chriſt, nor the Father, nor the Holy Ghoſt but my ſelf, and thoſe that believe in this Commiſsion of the Spirit; for it is not with me as it is with you, for you are to be judged by the letter of the Scriptures, but God hath made me the Judge of Scriptures and of you alſo.</p>
            <p>For my Commiſsion and the Doctrine of it is as true as the Prophets and Apoſtles Commiſsions were in their time; nay, it is of a more higher nature than theirs were: For we the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Spirit do know more than <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, or Apoſtles did, things of more higher concernment, As</p>
            <p>To know the form and nature of the true God before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came fleſh. The form and nature of the right Devil before he be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fleſh. The perſons and nature of Angels. The riſe of the two Seeds. What knowledge can exceed, or go beyond the knowledge of the true God and the righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Devil, many other deep Secrets which hath been declared by this Commiſſion of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which the Prophets and Apoſtles were but dark in, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Witneſſes of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>If ſo, how ſhould you <hi>Quakers</hi> come to underſtand any thing concerning Chriſt, the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, who have nothing but the dead letter of other mens words, whoſe light was but dark in compariſon of that light that comes by this Commiſſion of the Spirit, ſo that you can never know Chriſt, nor the Father, nor the Holy Ghoſt, by the words of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor by the light of Chriſt within you, without an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there being none in the world at this day but my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Can your light within you make theſe three you ſpeak of, Chriſt, the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, to be but one perſon and particular body of fleſh and bone in the form of a man? if you can, then may you truly ſay that you know the Father, Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt, which I know no <hi>Quaker</hi> or other doth, or can know at this day, but this Commiſsion of the Spirit onely; Neither can any man by the light of Chriſt within him, come to know theſe things aforeſaid, but by believing of him that's ſent by voice of words from a God without him.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Quakers</hi> were never ſent from a God without them, but onely from a Light within them, and though it be the light
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62519:14"/>
of Chriſt, yet will it not give a man the knowledge of the true God, but will periſh; and he that hath it, except it be grounded by faith to believe that God ſpake to ſuch a man to the hearing of the ear, and then the light of Chriſt in a man being ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon that voice, he ſhall come to know the Father, Son, and Spirit, to be but one perſonal Glory in the form of a man, which no <hi>Quaker</hi> in the world doth, therefore cannot know the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt by that light within them which they talk ſo much of: for a childe that anſwers from his Catechiſm-book would have ſaid as much from the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> do, for a boy could have rehearſed theſe places of Scripture, and have made as good a Confeſſion of his faith as any <hi>Quaker</hi> doth. But let that paſs, and come to the next.</p>
            <p n="5">5. You ſay further, that I have written, <hi>The Quakers will have no perſon at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words in your Letter to this is not worth a Reply; for there is little in it but the repeating of Scripture words, and what the Apoſtle ſaith of Chriſt being the expreſs image of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers perſon; which if it were but opened, it would utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their own principles of the light of Chriſt within them, which they are very angry with me for ſaying that the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them will vaniſh like ſmoke, which they will finde to be true: but I ſhall go to the next.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You ſay I write, that a great part of you are of thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Ranters, that have been given over to blood-ſhed with a ſword of ſteel, or elſe to all manner of luſts of the fleſh, and now I ſay you think by a preciſe and exactneſs of life to recover your peace with God, and yet deny the very perſon of God without you.</p>
            <p>Your Anſwer to this Sentence of mine is ſomething large, but moſt of it rayling and rehearſing the ſame words as were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before; for you make a great deal of do about knowing the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, and keep a ſtir about Chriſts being the expreſs image of the Fathers perſon, and yet all this while you cannot finde out any perſon of God at all; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you have gotten <hi>Pauls</hi> words, and run away with them as a dog doth with a bone: for the letter of the Scriptures is caſt down as a bone by the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Chriſt himſelf;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62519:14"/>
for how would <hi>Quakers</hi> have done to have found out theſe words, <hi>That Chriſt is the expreſs image of the Fathers perſon,</hi> if <hi>Paul</hi> had not ſaid ſo? I marvel how they would have known that Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteneth every man that cometh into the world, if they had not found ſuch words in Scripture.</p>
            <p>But thoſe men that ſpake the Scriptures know what the light of Chriſt was, theſe can onely ſpeak of it, but know nothing truely what the light of Chriſt is, nor from whence it doth ariſe.</p>
            <p>There is one expreſſion in this part of your Letter which would make one laugh, which is this, <hi>Doth the devil rage in me becauſe ſome who have been Ranters and uſed outward weapons former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, now they are turned from theſe things, and turned unto God, and Chriſt the expreſs image of the Fathers perſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe Ranters that are turned to God and Chriſt in the Quakers way, they had better have kept themſelves where they were; for before they were in the wilderneſs, but are now turned back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſo are further off from entring into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that is a place of reſt for their ſouls, than they were before: So that the ſtate of the <hi>Quakers</hi> is more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to be ſaved than the Ranters; for if they turn a right <hi>Quaker</hi> after they have been at the Rant, there is no poſsibility for them to be ſaved, for they are two-fold more the children of the Devil than they were before: For if ſuch a <hi>Quaker</hi> ſhould give his goods to the poor, and his body to be burnt for that light within him, it will avail him nothing; for there are but theſe three ſtates in man, <hi>Egypt,</hi> the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by faith in a Commiſsion, and they that truly believe in a Commiſsion, are the Saints that Chriſt dwells in, and not the <hi>Quakers;</hi> for they are for the moſt part of them, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the children of <hi>Cain,</hi> who was of that wicked one, which always was in bondage, and there ſhall remain to eternity. So much in anſwer to your railing Letter.</p>
            <p>Now I have given you anſwer to your curſed blaſphemy and railing ſpeeches againſt thoſe Truths which I have ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you <hi>Quakers,</hi> it remains that I ſhould give anſwer to your Queries, which are many. There are Queries enough, if an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, to make a Volumn bigger than the Bible; for there hath been greater Volumns than the Bible made of one of thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62519:15"/>
Texts of Scripture which you have propounded, by wiſe men in reaſon.</p>
            <p>But this ſeemeth to be a marvellous thing, that you <hi>Quakers</hi> that are guided by the light of Chriſt within you, and knows the minde of Chriſt and the Apoſtles doctrine, and knoweth the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, and Chriſt the expreſs image of the Fathers perſon, in that you ſhould be ignorant of the knowledge of theſe things which you propound unto me to anſwer, elſe I muſt ſtop my mouth for ever.</p>
            <p>Ce tainly if you had known them your ſelves, you would not have propounded them to me to anſwer; neither is it the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peity of him that hath true knowledge in him to put queſtions to another, which he cannot anſwer himſelf. It is a thing I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did to any ſince I came to know the truth, I never did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound any queſtion to any man that I could not anſwer my ſelf; though I have been asked many queſtions by ſeveral ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet never any went empty away without an anſwer; ſome ſatisfied, and ſome unſatisfied, becauſe they could not queſtion any further; nay, there hath not been that queſtion that could ariſe out of the heart of man, let it be what it would concerning ſpiritual things, with relation to God, Devil, Heaven, Hell, or any other ſpiritual thing, but I have given anſwer to it. Nay, ſome have gone ſo far as to ask who made God, and I have given anſwer to that alſo.</p>
            <p>N thing hath been too hard for me in ſpiritual things, if it hath been propounded in Engliſh words. When I ſay ſpiritual things, I ſpeak with relation to the knowledge of the true God his form and nature before he became fleſh, and what he is now in himſelf. And what the right devil was before he became fleſh, and what he is now in himſelf, and how Heaven and Hell doth depend upon theſe two, with the knowledge of the perſons and nature of the Angels, and the mortality of the ſoul. On theſe ſix Principles depend all ſpiritual and heavenly knowledge, with many other heavenly ſecrets, which floweth as a river of living water from thoſe ſix heads, which no Quaker doth or can know in that ſtate of being a Quaker, nor any other Opinion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion whatſoever, but thoſe that do believe in this Commiſsion of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62519:15"/>And as for thoſe eighteen Queries that you have propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thoſe that are of the moſt higheſt concernment, they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and opened at large in our Writings already. And ſome of your Queries are of ſuch a long nature, that they are not worth the labor to anſwer, neither would there be any great edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to any that ſhould know them, yet I ſhall give a word or two to the firſt part of your third Querie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For what end did Chriſt come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt came into the world for this very end, for to deſtroy him that had the power of death, which is the Devil, which Devil is the ſeed or ſpirit of Reaſon in man, of which ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Reaſon which is the Devil, moſt part of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are of his ſeed, and Chriſt came into the world for to deſtroy, that is, to deſtroy the ſeed of the Serpent with an eternal death, and to raiſe the ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> up to a more happier eſtate than that was wherein he was created.</p>
            <p>This could not be accompliſhed but by Gods coming down f om Heaven into the womb of a Virgin, and ſo became a childe in pure mortality, and when he grew up to be a man, according to the Scriptures, he was capable to ſuffer the pains of death, and ſo paſs through death, and quickening into life again in the ſame body, he got power over death, in that death was not able to keep him under; and ſo got power over him that had the power of death in his hands, which is the devil.</p>
            <p>This devil ſo much ſpoken of in Scripture, is no other but the ſpirit of Reaſon, which was firſt in <hi>Cain,</hi> he killing righteous <hi>Abel</hi> had p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer to kill, that is, power to put to death, and ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th entred into the world; for death never was in the world before the Serpent beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> then entred death into the world; and <hi>Cain</hi> being the firſt-born of the devil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he had the power of death in his hands, and it doth remain in his hands to this day.</p>
            <p>But happy are the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> that hath ſo much faith as to believe that it was the very God-head life that ſuffered death, and ſo overcame death by his quickening into life again, and ſo hath gained to himſelf a greater power and glory than he had before death entred i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to the world; for by his riſing again, he hath got power to raiſe the ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> to a more happy and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62519:16"/>
glorious eſtate than that was wherein he was created.</p>
            <p>He hath gotten power alſo to deſtroy him that had the power of death in his hands, that is, to keep the ſeed of Reaſon in a more low and ſad eſtate then that was wherein he was created, even under the ſecond or eternal death, which could not have been but by the death and riſe again of God himſelf; and for this very end did Chriſt come into the world.</p>
            <p>It would have been well for you and many thouſands more, if Chriſt had never come into the world at all; for your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation is procured by it.</p>
            <p>I could open what is meant by the light of Chriſt, and how it may be ſaid that Chriſt enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, but it would be too large, beſides it is fully open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Book of ours, called, <hi>A Divine Looking-Glaſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eves</hi> eſtate before the fall, and after their fall, that is plainly declared in <hi>The Interpretation of the</hi> 11. <hi>of the Revelation.</hi> The Tree of Life, and the Knowledge of good and evil, and of the Serpent, and of the woman that fled into the wilderneſs, and what the time, and times, and half a time is, and of the Beaſt, with many other things opened, and Scriptures expounded of a far more high concernment than thoſe things you propounded. I ſay theſe things are largely opened in <hi>The Interpretation of the ſaid</hi> 11 <hi>Chapter of the Revelation,</hi> and in <hi>The Divine Looking-Glaſs,</hi> wherein are written the deepeſt myſteries that ever was penn'd, if underſtood by the Reader.</p>
            <p>Alſo there is the Mortality of the Soul, that doth ſhew what is Scripture, and what is not, and how the Soul of man is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, but muſt, and doth dye. Alſo there is that called, <hi>Look about you, for the Devil that you fear is within you.</hi> And a Dialogue between Faith and Reaſon, and the <hi>Quakers Downfal.</hi> There is hardly any thing that is neceſſary to be known concerning the ſpiritual eſtate of mankinde, but it is to be found in ſome of theſe Writings.</p>
            <p>Therefore if any of you <hi>Quakers</hi> have a minde to be any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther informed of your Queries, they muſt look into thoſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings afore-mentioned; for there is very few of your Queries that are not anſwered in one kinde or another. But I know you <hi>Quakers</hi> do not regard looking into any other writings but your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62519:16"/>
own, therefore I ſhall not perſwade you unto it, but let you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in your own conceited light of Chriſt within you.</p>
            <p>But you will finde it to be the greateſt darkneſs of all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches, becauſe it is the very ſpirit of Antichriſt, or the Devil transformed into an Angel of light, that is it carryeth the pureſt ſhew of holineſs of life, and ſuffereth more than any other doth for his Religion, and yet the moſt curſedſt of all in point of doctrine; for they are the greateſt fighters againſt Gods being a perſon, by that light within them, of any. Neither will there ever come any more ſpirits of Antichriſt ſo Angel-like, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> do, for they have received the ſpirits of Antichriſt new in this laſt Age, as I ſaid before, and it will continue to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> you might have ſet your name as well as two Letters, but it matters not now.</p>
            <p>I have given Anſwer to your railing Letter you ſent to me for ſpeaking the truth. For there is not one jot or tittle of my words in thoſe ſix Principles or Sentences of mine concerning the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> that ſhall fail and not come to paſs, but are as true as any thing that ever was ſpoken by Prophet or Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſhall ſpeak a few words unto you two in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, becauſe you two have committed that unpardonable ſin that never will be forgiven in this world, nor in the world to come; for you have done deſpite unto the Spirit of Truth, in ſpeaking evil of things you do not know, for you have called the Doctrine and Declaration of the Spirit, <hi>Blaſphemy, Deceit,</hi> and <hi>Lies,</hi> with many other railing ſpeeches, with high impudency, from a light within you, and from the dead letter without you, and hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly lifted up your ſelves with that light within you, to ſpeak evil of the Commiſſion of the Spirit, which we received from the true perſonal God without us, even the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory. Therefore in obedience to my Commiſsion, I do pronounce <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> for this their Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent me, curſed and damned ſoules and bodies from the preſence of God, elect men and Angels, to eternity.</p>
            <p>Your Light within you, nor God without you ſhall deliver you from this Sentence which I have declared upon you, becauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62519:17"/>
you ſhall know that there is a true Prophet now in the laſt Age, as well as there hath been in former times. And this Sentence ſhall be the mark of your Reprobation in your foreheads to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, even as your great Grandfather had in his forehead; and all the Seed of Faith that ſhall read this Epiſtle and ſee you, ſhall ſee the mark of Reprobation in your foreheads, neither ſhall you ſcrape it out, but it will be ſeen by the Elect as long as you live.</p>
            <p>And when you dye, you ſhall paſs through this firſt death into the ſecond death, and in the Reſurrection you ſhall never ſee the face of God, nor man, nor Angels, nor your own faces, to eternity: but you ſhall be in utter darkneſs, where is weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth for evermore</p>
            <p>And though you think you ſhall have never a body, you are deceived: you ſhall have a ſpiritual dark body which ſhall be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to bear thoſe eternal torments, and you ſhall remember you were told ſo by a Prophet.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Written by</hi> Lodowick Muggleton, <hi>one of the two Laſt Witneſſes and Prophets unto the High and Mighty God the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>November 3. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Have publiſhed your Lettter to as many of the Believers of this Commiſſion of the Spirit, as I have had opportunity to meet with them; ſo I do expect that you ſhould read mine unto as many of the <hi>Quakers</hi> as you ſhall have the like opportunity.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>For <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <trailer>Let this be ſent to <hi>Thomas Highfield</hi> at <hi>Notingham,</hi> to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the aboveſaid.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62519:17"/>
            <head>A LETTER of <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> to <hi>Lodowick Muggleton.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Falſe Judgement reverſed and againſt teſtified by <hi>Rich: Farnſworth,</hi> in Anſwer to <hi>Lodowick Muggleton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Lodowick Muggleton,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou who pretends to have received a Commiſſion by voice of words to the hearing of the ear, from a God w thout thee, to curſe Angels or men to eternity: And ſayeſt thou art the Witneſs of the Spirit, and the laſt Witneſs that ever ſhall ſpeak by Commiſsion from God whileſt the world endureth. And ſayeſt, God hath ordained thee the Chief Judge in the world at this day, to give ſentence upon men and women ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and eternal, and what ſhall become of them after death. And in obedience to thy pre ended Commiſsion, ſayeſt, thou haſt already curſed and damned many hundreds of ſouls and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from the preſence of God, elect men and Angels, to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and that thou rejoyceſt in the Condemnation of them, and art wondrous well ſatisfied in giving Judgement upon them. By which it appears, thou wouldſt be both Judge, Accuſer, and Witneſs thy ſelf, to condemn without any right order, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to truth at thy will and pleaſure, which is Antichriſtian and very erroneous: But Error in Judgement ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and holden for nothing, as thine is, who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy pretended Commiſſion, art diſcovered to be a falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and in deluſion, as is apparent and manifeſt in ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, in a Reply of Mine to that of Thine bearing date <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> the 10. 1662. written by thee in Anſwer to <hi>Edward Bournes</hi> to <hi>Dorothy Carter.</hi> But ſince I have ſeen four ſheets of paper written by thee, dated <hi>November</hi> the 3. 1662. and directed to <hi>Thomas Highfield</hi> in <hi>Notingham,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> which coming to my hands in <hi>Notingham</hi> the 22th day of the ninth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62519:18"/>
month, 1662. (being then priſoner there) I carefully peruſed over, which I found to be of like nature the other was of. In both which, or all of thoſe Writings of thine, I have found therein contained, implyed, aſſerted and affirmed by thee, as is apparent unto me, and evident againſt thee, theſe neceſſary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions hereafter following, which may be a ſufficient diſcovery of thee, and teſtimony or warning againſt thee.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That under pretence of a Commiſſion of the Spirit, thou haſt abuſed, belyed, and wronged the Spirit, by preſuming in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame and authority of the Spirit, to ſet up thy ſelf as Judge, Accuſer, and Witneſs, to condemn at thy will and pleaſure all ſuch as are beloved, bleſſed, and juſtified of God, and his Holy Spirit, who cannot receive thy errors for truth, but deny them, and teſtifie againſt thee for appearing in the ſame under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Commiſſion in thy imagination, pride, and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe thou ſayeſt, thou art both Judge and Witneſs. And the Accuſer thou art, and falſe Witneſs alſo, who ſayeſt, That never a one that thou haſt curſed, ſhall eſcape that curſe which thou haſt denounced upon them. And that if an Angel from heaven ſhould come and ſay thou haſt ſpoken falſe, or lyed in the doctrine which thou haſt declared, thou haſt power to curſe Angels or men to eternity. And further ſayeſt, that no God will deliver from thy Sentence; All which ſayings of thine are falſe and erroneous, and therefore undone and holden by me for nothing, but as thy errors, falſe judgement, deluſion, pride, and preſumption.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That under pretence of a Commiſſion from God, thou haſt preſumed in thy imagination and pride of thy heart, to exalt thy ſelf above God and Chriſt, and to take all pardoning power from them, becauſe thou accounts if thy Sentence and Judgement be once pronounced and paſt, though never ſo erroneous and falſe, that they might not be able to reverſe, and undo the ſame. Thou preſumes to take all pardoning power from God and Chriſt in that caſe, becauſe thou ſayeſt no infinite Spirit of Chriſt, nor any god can, or ſhall be able to deliver from thy Sentence and Curſe, which is thy error and lying divination, or falſe doctrine, pride, and preſumption, as is apparent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That under pretence of a Commiſsion from the Spirit, thou
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62519:18"/>
preſumes in thy imagination to be ſingular in doctrine, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, judgement, and power above all men, either Prophets or Apoſtles ſince the beginning of the world, or that ever ſhall be hereafter whilſt the world doth endure.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That under pretence of a Commiſsion of the Spirit, thou preſumes to exclude all true Witneſſes of the Spirit, and alſo all true Miniſters, Meſſengers, and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt from the work of the Miniſtery, both now in this Age, and whileſt the world doth endure, to the end and intent thou mayeſt ſet up thy ſelf alone in their places and ſtead, becauſe thou preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſayeſt, That God hath made thee the Judge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and hath given thee underſtanding of his minde in the Scriptures above all men in the world, or above all men ſince the world began. That no man doth know the Scriptures but thy ſelf. That no man can truely interpret Scriptures but thy ſelf. That God hath given the Scriptures into thy hand, as he gave the Prieſts Office into the hands of <hi>Aaron.</hi> That no man ought to officiate the Office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger, or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of Chriſt, but thoſe that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf. That thou knows more then <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, or Apoſtles did. That thy Doctrine and the Commiſsion of it, is as true, and of a higher nature than the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles was in their time. That thy Commiſsion, and the doctrine of it, is of a higher nature than that of the Prophet <hi>Elijahs</hi> was, when he commanded four hundred prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> to be ſlain, by the power of his word. That thou art the laſt Witneſs that ever ſhall ſpeak by Commiſsion from God. And that God will never chuſe any more after thee, whileſt the world endureth; All which are thy errors and lies, which are by me denyed, and againſt teſtified.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That (under pretence of thy Commiſsion) thou haſt brought forth a Doctrine contrary to truth, and that the ſame Doctrine ought not to be entertained or received by <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> nor none upon the earth, becauſe thou ſayeſt thou art the laſt Witneſs and Prophet that ever ſhall ſpeak by Commiſsion from God; and there is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of thy Doctrine, becauſe thou ſayeſt there is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of the Doctrine of a Prophet who hath a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62519:19"/>
Commiſsion from God. And there neither is, nor ſhall be any ſuch Prophet (thou ſayeſt) but thy ſelf, whileſt the world endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. And alſo ſayeſt, That neither <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> nor no man upon the earth can, or ought to judge of thy Doctrine, becauſe thou ſayeſt that neither ſhe, nor no man upon the earth can, or ought to judge of the Doctrine of a Prophet who hath a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion from God: And ſayeſt, there neither is, nor ſhall be any ſuch Prophet but thy ſelf, as aforeſaid. And to exclude <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy Carter,</hi> and all men upon earth from judgement in point of Doctrine, is to exclude them from reception thereof, and ſo from the reward, if any be due; which is contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Truth, which ſaith, <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.21. <hi>And try the Spirits whether they be of God, becauſe many falſe prophets are gone out into the world,</hi> 1 John 4.1. And how can doctrines be proved, and ſpirits be tryed, if none he capable to judge thereof, who are to receive? By this it is apparent, that thou art unwilling to have thy doctrine proved, and ſpirit tryed, leſt upon tryal and proof thou be found out to be a falſe prophet, which thou art, as is apparent enough.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That there is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of thy Doctrine, and that none upon the earth can or ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame, becauſe thou haſt excluded them all off from judgement in order to reception thereof; by which its apparent, that under pretence of thy Commiſsion, thou labors to exclude <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> and all men upon earth from ſalvation, which makes it evident againſt thee, that thou art a meſſenger of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and not of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That thou preſumes under pretence of thy Commiſsion of the Spirit, to rob Chriſt of his Office which his Father hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him, as Chief Judge ordained of God; becauſe thou ſayeſt, thou art chief Judge in the world ordained of God, to give Judgement upon men and women ſpiritual and eternal, and what ſhall become of them after death, which is but thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, pride, and falſe doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. For Chriſt Jeſus who is the faithful Witneſs, and Prince of the Kings of the earth, he hath all Judgement com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him, becauſe it is written concerning him, <hi>That the Father hath committed all Judgement unto him,</hi> John 5.22. <hi>And
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62519:19"/>
hath given him Authority to execute Judgement, becauſe he is the Son,</hi> as it is written, <hi>John</hi> 5.27.</p>
            <p>But it is no where written in the Scriptures of Truth concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee, <hi>Lodowick</hi> that all Judgement either is, or ſhall be (by the Father) committed unto thee, to pronounce the Sentence of eternal death and damnation upon the ſouls and bodies of men to eternity, as thou haſt done. Whereby it appears thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt exclude Chriſt from his Office (in point of Judgement) which the Father hath committed unto him, and are thereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be a falſe witneſs, and meſſenger of Satan.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lodowick,</hi> thou art not the chief Judge in the world at this day ordained of God, as aforeſaid. Thy Meſſage and Teſtimony is falſe and not true, becauſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue Witneſſes of the Spirit, and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt who were Anointed and Sealed of God, have declared and ſaid, That God hath appointed a day in the which he will judge the world in righteouſneſs, (not by thee, but) by Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead, as may be read <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30, 31.</p>
            <p>And becauſe God hath ordained Chriſt Jeſus to be Judge of all men, and hath given them aſſurance of the ſame, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead, thou <hi>Lodowick,</hi> art not that Judge ordained of God, becauſe thou art not Chriſt Jeſus which was raiſed from the dead; neither hath God given that aſſurance to all men of thee, that he gave of Chriſt; by raiſing him from the dead, as aforeſaid. Here I charge thee to be a falſe judge, and a falſe prophet, that ran but never was ſent of the Lord. Thy judgement and doctrine is very erroneous and falſe, as is plainly manifeſt againſt thee, and is therefore reverſed.</p>
            <p>They who were the true and faithful Witneſſes and Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of Chriſt, who were anointed and ſealed of God, and had a Commiſsion of God, they did not preſume to take the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, as Judge ordained of God, from Chriſt, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it to themſelves, as thou moſt unjuſtly haſt done, whereby thou haſt appeared to be a falſe prophet, and meſſenger of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</p>
            <p>For they who were anointed and ſealed of God, who were the true Witneſſes of the Spirit, and had a Commiſsion from Chriſt,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62519:20"/>
to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs, they witneſs againſt thee, by teſtifying on the behalf of Chriſt, that he commanded them to preach unto the people, and to teſtifie that it is he who was ordained of God to be Judge of the quick and the dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42.</p>
            <p>Firſt by their Commiſsion they were to preach to the people. And ſecondly by the ſame Commiſsion they were to teſtifie to them, that Chriſt was ordained of God to be the Judge both of quick and dead; Therefore thou art not Judge, becauſe thou art not Chriſt, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou accuſedſt the Quakers to be of the nature and ſeed of the Serpent, and gave judgement againſt them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, thou haſt cleared them from the ſame by thy ſelf-confutation, and ſelf-contradiction, wherein thou ſayeſt, That the <hi>Quakers</hi> do preach from the Scriptures and light within, and that devils are caſt out, and much good is done by them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Quakees</hi> (ſo called) do preach from the Scriptures and light within.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe they ſo preach, they are ſent of God; for how ſhall they preach, except they be ſent?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That by vertue of their preaching, and the power which they have received of God, devils are caſt out, and much good is done by them; and ſuch are not of the nature and ſeed of the Serpent.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt cleared them from the ſame by thy ſelf-confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then to what purpoſe is all thy falſe Judgement, and what ever thou haſt laid againſt them in thy preſumption, pride, and imagination? It is but error in judgement, and is therefore undone, (as I ſaid) and holden for nothing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written by <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> Quaker,</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>and ſent to <hi>Dorothy Carter</hi> to be directed to <hi>Lodowick Muggleton.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="reply_to_letter">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62519:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi>'s ANSWER to <hi>Richard Farnſworths</hi> Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Richard Farnſworth,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received a Paper from you, entituled, <hi>Falſe Judgement re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed and againſt teſtified, in Anſwer to</hi> Lodowick Muggleton. In anſwer to this Paper of yours, I ſhall firſt commend you in theſe two things, firſt, in that you have ſet your name to it; for I have a Letter from a Quaker in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> which hath neither ſet his Name, nor two letters, yet I have made a ſhift to ſend an Anſwer: but I had rather to have his name or two letters, as I had of <hi>W. S.</hi> The ſecond thing that I commend you for, is becauſe you have ſet down my words ſo truly and punctually, it makes my Commiſsion and Authority to ſhine the more bright and clear to all thoſe that underſtand the nature and power of a Commiſsion, though you in the cloſe of many of thoſe paſſages, have ſlighted, vilified, and ſpoken evil of thoſe things which are as true as Truth it ſelf, and that you ſhall find.</p>
            <p>And becauſe you are not under the Sentence of this Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Spirit, by verbal words or writing already, I ſhall give Anſwer to your Letter; for I never do give anſwer in writing to any one that is under the Sentence of this Commiſsion, for he is but as a condemned man; neither is it the practice of any earthly Judge after he hath condemned a man to die, for to treat any more with him that is ſo condemned, neither can that man get the Judge to revoke it: but perhaps a man ſo condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Law may make ſuit to the King, which is above the Law, and ſo may get his pardon, but that is ſeldom known. But it is not ſo with thoſe that are condemned by the Commiſsion of the Spirit, becauſe no condemned perſon can make his Appeal unto God, the King of Heaven, neither by himſelf nor by any other, becauſe God the King of Heaven is not in this world at all; therefore he hath commiſſionated mortal men to be Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62519:21"/>
Miniſters, and Ambaſſadors, to treat with mortal men about their ſpiritual and eternal eſtate, and every true Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador ſtands in Gods ſtead, and hath power to condemn and to ſave alive, that is, to bleſs to eternity, and to curſe to eternity: And this power hath God given unto us two the choſen Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Spirit, neither can God take it again, becauſe God hath ſpoken it, and cannot lye; for he ſaid theſe words, That he had choſen us two his laſt Meſſengers unto this bloody unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving world, and that he had put the Two edged Sword of his Spirit into our mouthes, that who ever was pronounced bleſſed through our mouthes, are bleſſed to eternity: So on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who ever we pronounce curſed through our mouthes, are curſed to eternity: and this I know God cannot revoke, becauſe he is Truth, and cannot lye.</p>
            <p>Therefore to give Anſwer to thoſe deſpiſing, ſlighting, and vilifying words of yours in your Letter againſt thoſe Truths which you have ſet down, which was written to <hi>Edward Bourne,</hi> and the four ſheets which I ſent to <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> And in the firſt part of your Letter you have ſhewed what ſeed and nature you are of, even as <hi>Edward Bournes,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Hooton,</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> have done, you being of the ſame ſeed as they are of, that is the ſeed of the Serpent, which muſt go the ſame way as your father <hi>Cain</hi> which begot you, muſt go; for you have blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent me, by calling the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this Commiſsion of the Spirit Antichriſtian, and very Erroneous, and a falſe prophet, and a Deluſion, with many other wicked ſpeeches thoroughout your paper, which is a clear teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and diſcovery unto me that you are the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſo guided and led by the ſpirit of Antichriſt now in this laſt Age of the world.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that you do accuſe in me to be falſe is, that you ſay that under the pretence of a Commiſſion of the Spirit, that I have abuſed, belyed, and wronged the Spirit, by preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the Name and Authority of the Spirit to ſet up my ſelf as Judge, Accuſer and Witneſs, to condemn at my will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all ſuch as are beloved, bleſſed, and juſtified of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That my Commiſſion of the Spirit is no pretended thing, but as true as ever <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Apoſtles Commiſſion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62519:21"/>
was, and of as great, my of a greater authority than theirs was, and given by the ſame Spirit of Truth as theirs was; Neither have I ſet up my ſelf as a Judge, Accuſer, or Witneſs, but God hath ſet me up to be the chief Judge in the world at this day; for he hath ſet me in his ſtead to be Judge, Accuſer, and Witneſs, to judge and condemn Antichriſtian ſpirits, that doth deny God to be a diſtinct perſon of himſelf of fleſh and bone, and all blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſpirits which ſinneth againſt the Holy Ghoſt. Theſe two things there is more of the <hi>Quakers</hi> doth commit, than any other Sects whatſoever, therefore there is great need that God ſhould make ſome mortal man Judge of theſe conceited, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born-hearted people called <hi>Quakers;</hi> neither are thoſe people the beloved, bleſſed, and juſtified of God, but the moſt curſedſt of God of all other Sects, neither doth any other Sect fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods being in the form of a man, as they do; for they have got Chriſt within them, but doth abhor that he ſhould have fleſh and bone of his own without them: and by this Chriſt which is fleſh and bone glorified without me, am I made Judge of mens ſpiritual eſtate, neither ſhall any one that I have condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſee any other God or Judge but that Sentence which we the Witneſſes of the Spirit have paſſed upon them.</p>
            <p>And though you call it preſumption, and a thing undone and holden by you as nothing but errors, falſe judgement, pride and ſuch like, yet you ſhall finde it to be as true as if God had judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you himſelf; for this I can boldly ſay, that I am, as true an Ambaſſador of God, and Judge of mens ſpiritual eſtate, as ever any was ſince the Creation of the world: and if you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others can ſatisfie your ſelves that there never was any man commiſſionated of God to bleſs and curſe, then you ſhall eſcape that Curſe that I have pronounced upon ſo many hundreds, and I onely ſhall ſuffer for curſing others, without a Commiſion from God, but I know by what authority I do theſe things, and ſo I am at perfect reſt; as to my Eternal happineſs, in that I have heen obedient unto my Commiſſion which was given of God by voyce of words, to the hearing of the Ear.</p>
            <p n="2">2 You ſay, that I under pretence of a Commiſſion from God, have preſumed in my imaginations, and pride in my heart, to exalt my ſelf above God and Chriſt, and to take all pardoning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62519:22"/>
power from them, becauſe ſay you, that I account of my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and Judgment, if once pronounced and paſt, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo erroneous and falſe, that they might not be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and undo the ſame: that I preſume to take all pardoning power from God and Chriſt in that caſe, becauſe I ſay no infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Spirit of Chriſt, nor any God can, or ſhall be able to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from my Sentence and Curſe, which you <hi>Quakers</hi> doth ſay theſe ſayings aforeſaid is my error, and lying divination, or falſe doctrine, pride and preſumption, as is apparent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That my Commiſſion is no pretended thing, but as true as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and as the Apoſtles Commiſſion was, and <hi>John Reeve</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> are ordained and choſen of God by voice of words, and commiſsionated with power as realy and truly as ever <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> was. And as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were the choſen Meſſengers and Commiſsioners of the Law, ſo likewiſe are we the two choſen Witneſſes and Commiſsioners of the Spirit: And as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were the two firſt which God choſe to give forth the Law, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe Rules of Worſhip for the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo likewiſe we two being the two laſt choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, we have power and authority in this Commiſsion of the Spirit, for to declare what the true God is in his form and nature, and what worſhip doth belong to the knowledge of the true God in theſe latter days, which cannot be known but by this Commiſsion of the Spirit onely.</p>
            <p>And as for my taking of all pardoning power from God and Chriſt, in this you ſhew that you have gone no further, nor hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo far as the Prieſts of the Nation; for you have got a God and a Chriſt too, and yet neither your God nor your Chriſt hath never a body, and in this you are worſe than any other Sect: for though other Sects of Religion will have a God and a Chriſt, yet they can finde but one body, and that is the body of Chriſt, but the Fathers body they cannot finde at all: but you <hi>Quakers</hi> can finde never a body neither for God nor Chriſt but your own bodies, for you have got your Chriſt and God all within you; ſo that Chriſt hath never a body of his own, but is forc'd to make uſe of every <hi>Quakers</hi> body for his Spirit to dwell in. But from that Chriſt which ſuffered death in his own body, and roſe again
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62519:22"/>
in the ſame body, and is now in Heaven in the ſame body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, from this Chriſt which is the onely God, I ſay I have power over all other Gods or infinite Spirits whatſoever, and from this Chriſt which is God-Man now above the ſtars, have I this pardoning power and damning power, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I take it of my ſelf, but it was put upon me by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: for if I had not obeyed the voice of God when he ſpake to <hi>John Reeve,</hi> then he was to pronounce me curſed to eternity, and ſo by my yielding obedience unto the voice of God, I was made partakers of that power to bleſs and curſe to eternity: and this is that power which you ſay I preſumptuouſly have exalted my ſelf; neither will God give this power to any more after me, neither can any man come to the aſſurance of the favor of God now in theſe days, but in believing that God gave this power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf; for there is no coming to know God, nor ſee God, but by the faith in this Commiſsion of the Spirit: for I having the Keys of Heaven and of Hell, none can get into Heaven except the Witneſs of the Spirit doth open the gates, and ſo the King of Glory may enter in, that is, the knowledge of the true God his form and nature may enter into your hearts, by having faith in this Commiſsion of the Spirit: for God hath given me the ſame power now, as he gave to <hi>Peter</hi> when he was upon earth, and what power that was may eaſily be read where Chriſt ſaid unto <hi>Peter, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build my Church.</hi> Alſo he hid give unto <hi>Peter</hi> the Keys of Heaven and of Hell. Alſo he ſhould have power to binde and looſe, and whoſe ſins he remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhould be remitted, and whoſe ſins he retained ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. What is the remitting and retaining of ſins, but to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them their ſins which received his Doctrine, and to retain and binde their ſins of unbelief more cloſe upon their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for their deſpiſing of the Doctrine of Chriſt which he did teach? And was this any leſs than bleſsing and curſing, or ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the gates of Hell and of Heaven? and yet you ſee that Chriſt gave this power unto man: you would have ſaid as much by <hi>Peter</hi> and others, if you had been living in thoſe days, as you do by me: you would have ſaid that they did it out of the pride and preſumption of their hearts, though they had their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion put upon them by God himſelf, as I have now in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62519:23"/>
of the Spirit: and as <hi>Peter</hi> had power to bind and looſe, or to remit and to retain, ſo likewiſe hath the ſame God given me power to bleſs and curſe men and women to eternity: and this is the keys of Heaven and of Hell; for the bleſsing of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsionated Prophet it opens the gate of heaven, that is, it opens the heart in love to that God that ſent ſuch a Meſſenger of glad tidings of Salvation: So on the contrary, the curſe of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet it opens the gates of Hell, that is, it opens the heart in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, malice and revenge; nay ſometimes when the gate of Hell is opened by the curſe, it hath cauſed revenge to increaſe ſo hot, that it hath broken forth into a great flame, the fire of Hell hath been ſo hot burning within them. This I know by experience, which I never did know until the Keys of Heaven and of Hell were put into my hands by God himſelf, and by this I know what <hi>Peters</hi> and other Prophets power was; for God hath given pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for one creature to judge another, and what that man doth which hath authority from God, God himſelf cannot undo it; for it is not the light of Chriſt within you <hi>Quakers,</hi> nor the letter of the Scriptures, nor God without you, that ſhall deliver you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others that are under this Sentence, from that curſe which I have pronounced upon you, though you call it error, lying divination, falſe doctrine, pride and preſumption: but it will appear to be no other but the Curſe of God himſelf, though it be pronounced by a mortal man like your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And as for my being ſingular in doctrine knowledge, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Power above all men, either Prophets, or Apoſtles ſince the beginning of the world, or that ſhall ever be hereafter, whilſt the world doth endure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This is as true a ſaying as ever was ſpoken, for this being the Commiſsion of the Spirit, it hath more ſpiritual knowledge, judgment, and power above all men either Prophets, or Apoſtles, why? becauſe <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets did not know ſo much as the Apoſtles did, becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> Commiſſion was that of the Law, under the title of God the Father, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith concerning thoſe that were educated under the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they were under a cloud, and ſaw but darkly as in a Glaſs, ſhewing the benefit which came to thoſe that were under the Faith of the Goſpel, for thoſe that were under the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62519:23"/>
Law, they were come but to Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> which gendred unto bondage, but thoſe that were come unto the Faith of the Goſpel, were come unto Mount <hi>Sion.</hi> Now the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> and the faith of the Goſpel of Jeſus was Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and this Goſpel of Jeſus which was committed to his Apoſtles, was the Commiſſion of the blood, and this Commiſſion of the blood, did know more then the Commiſſion of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets did, ſo likewiſe this Commiſſion of the Spirit, doth know more then either of them both; for <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets had no Scriptures for to interpret or expound, but their own propheſies, therefore the Apoſtles muſt needs know more then the Prophets did, becauſe they were the only inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the Law and the Prophets, and of their own ſigns, ſo therefore their knowledge in the Goſpel, muſt needs be greater then that of the Law; ſo likewiſe we the Witneſſes of the Spirit muſt needs know more then either Prophet or Apoſtle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none can interpret the Scriptures, but we the Witneſſes of the Spirit, and this Commiſſion of the Spirit did God force, and lay upon us againſt our wills, and withal he hath given us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his minde in the Scriptures above all the men in the world, which words of Gods I finde to prove true, for I do certainly know that I have more ſpiritual knowledge then all the men in the World, nay I am ſure that I do know more in ſpiritual things, then ever Prophet or Apoſtle did ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World, then of neceſſity it will follow that I do know more then any ſhall do to the end of the World, becauſe I am one of the two laſt Witneſſes and Prophets that God will ever ſend; therefore my knowledge, and judgement, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence muſt needs be above all that is gone before me, or that ſhall come after me to the end of the world, yet I am no ways lifted up with pride and preſumption becauſe of this knowledge and authority that God hath given me above all men ſince the beginning of the world, to the latter end.</p>
            <p>I know what I ſay to be truth, for true knowledge is never puffed up with pride, neither am I, whatſoever the ſeed of the ſerpent may judge of me, for I do neither bleſs any out of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections for any by ends, but according as I do diſcern their Faith in the thing, neither do I curſe any thorough envy or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62519:24"/>
malice, but either it is becauſe they have ſinned againſt the holy Spirit, a ſin that is not to be pardoned, or elſe I do know them to be of that reprobate ſeed, and ſo I know my judgement is true, and according to the tennor of my Commiſſion, ſo that I am nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lifted up with pride, nor caſt down, or troubled with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; but am very well ſatisfied in thoſe that go on the right hand, though they are but few, as I am with thoſe that go on the left hand, though they be many; for I ſee it muſt be ſo, for God hath ſo decreed it, and he hath been pleaſed to make it known unto me, and hath made me the onely Judge of the two ſeeds now in this laſt days, which is a thing I never did deſire.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is little of your matter in this particular, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing of my words, onely you ſay that I under the pretence of the Commiſſion of the ſpirit, that I do preſume to exclude all true Witneſſes of the Spirit, and alſo all true Miniſters, Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt from the work of the Miniſtry, both now in this age, and whileſt the world doth indure, to the end and intent that I might ſet up my ſelf alone in their places and ſtead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That my Commiſſion of the Spirit is no pretended thing, but as true as God is Truth, neither is there any true Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, Miniſter, or Ambaſſador of God in this world at this day but my ſelf, neither ſhall there be any ſent of God after me to the worlds end; for there can be no true Miniſter except he be ſent of God by voice of words to the hearing of the ear, or elſe by him that is ſo authorized; which I know no ſpeakers in the world hath, neither the Prieſts of the nation which are ordained by man, nor no other Sect, which by their natural wit, from the letter of the Scriptures, doth think becauſe they can play upon the letter of the Scriptures as upon a Harp, that they are very good Miniſters of Chriſt, but he ſent them not: and as for you <hi>Quakers,</hi> which thinkes the light of Chriſt within you, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make you Meſſengers and Miniſters of Chriſt, you are much miſtaken, for you do but run into the Miniſtry before you were ſent; for the light of Chriſt within a man did never autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize any man to be a Miniſter of Chriſt, except he be ordained and authorized from a God without him, or from a man without him, which you <hi>Quakers</hi> do abhor to think that there ſhould be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62519:24"/>
any other authority beſides the light of Chriſt within you, but you will finde that the authority of a God without you, will be too hard for the light of Chriſt within you.</p>
            <p>For little do you <hi>Quakers</hi> know what that Son of Man is which <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Revelation.</hi> 1.13. ſpeaketh of, ſo in the 16 verſe, <hi>There went out of his mouth a ſharp two-eged Sword.</hi> Now this Son of Man which <hi>John</hi> ſpeaketh of, was no other but Chriſt himſelf, and this Chriſt is the very God, and he is that <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt, he that was dead, and behold he is alive for evermore, and this two-edged ſword that came out of his mouth, he hath put into my mouth, and that was when he ſaid, I have put the two-edged Sword of my Spirit into thy mouth to pronounce bleſſing and curſing to eternity; now God having put the two-edged Sword of his Spirit which came out of his mouth, and hath put it into mine, how will you <hi>Quakers,</hi> or any others do to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver your ſelves from it? for it is a two-edged Sword, it cuts down the ſeed of faith, as the wheat in love, and makes it obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient unto the Commiſſion of the Spirit, and ſo they are gathered as Gods wheat into his barn, which barn is the Commiſsion of the Spirit, for every Commiſsion is a ſhelter, or as a barn to keep the wind, ſtorms, and rain off from the wheat: but on the contrary the other edge of this Sword which is put into my mouth, it cuts down the tares: the tares is the Seed of Reaſon, which are bound in bundles and caſt into the fire: for this edge of the Sword which is the ſentence of condemnation, it cuts down many bundles of the ſeed of reaſon for the fire of hel, to one ſheaf of the ſeed of faith which is gathered into Gods barn, that is, to believe the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Spirit. Now the <hi>Quakers</hi> and all other Sects, the ſpeakers of them, and many hundreds of their believers beſides, are thoſe tares which this Commiſsion of the Spirit hath cut down by the edge of this Sword, which ſhall be as bundles of tares fit for nothing elſe, but for that eternal fire, becauſe they have diſpiſed that their fellow creature ſhould have power to bleſs and curſe, though God will have men and women juſtified and condemned, no other way but by man like themſelves; for it was always Gods practice to give authority to men that are mortal, to Judge and Condemn according to the tenor of their Commiſsion, whether it be for a temporal death, or an eternal
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62519:25"/>
death: and this power hath God given unto me, and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I am the onely and alone Judge what ſhall become of men and women after death, neither ſhall thoſe that are damned by me, ſee any other God or Judge but me, or that ſentence which I have paſſed upon them: but the bleſſed ſhall ſee that God face to face, which hath ſet me as an Ambaſſador in his room, and this power I know God will never take from me, whatſoever you <hi>Quakers</hi> deny or teſtifie againſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5 There is little in this particular alſo, but my words repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, onely this, there is ſomething concerning <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> whereas I neither ſay that <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> nor no man upon the Earth can, or ought to judge of the doctrine of a Prophet, that hath a Commiſſion from God, there being none in the world at this day, but my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Who do you, blind <hi>Quakers,</hi> think ſhould be the Judge of a Prophet that hath a Commiſſion from God? is not a true Prophet the Law giver, and ought not every one to ſubmit unto his Laws? hath not a Prophet a prerogative power as a King hath? doth not a true Prophet ſtand in the King of Heavens room, as an Ambaſſador doth in the place of an earthly King? and ſhall thoſe that are to be ſubject to the Laws of the King, go to try whether the Kings Laws be good or juſt? nay thoſe that are the Kings Friends, ought not to try whether the Kings Laws or Declarations be juſt, becauſe his friends hapineſs lieth in yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience unto it; and if his Friends ought not to try the King, much leſs his enemies: ſo I ſay, though <hi>Dorothy Carter</hi> be a Friend to the Prophet of the Lord, that it lieth not in her power, neither is it for her to try the Doctrine of a Prophet, but to ſubmit unto the Doctrine and power of a Prophet, for therein lieth her, and all others ſafety. And whereas you ſay, that I have excluded <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> and all other men upon Earth, from ſalvation, I do here teſtifie, that ſhe is one of the bleſſed of the Lord, with many others in the world at this day, though I will not allow <hi>Dorothy Carter,</hi> nor no other, to have power to try a true Prophets Doctrine, though they be believers of it, that doth not exclude them from ſalvation, but gives them the more aſſurance of it, in that they ſuffer themſelves to be try'd by a Prophet, and his Doctrine; therefore I do exclude <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rothy Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62519:25"/>
and all men upon Earth in point of tryal or Judgment of the Doctrine of a Prophet that hath a Commiſſion from God, as I have, and if thoſe of the ſame Truth with a Prophet, may not try a Prophet, how will you do that are enemies to try his Doctrine? for it is not your quoting of the letters of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as you have done in two places, nor the light of Chriſt within you, that can try me; for I being one of the laſt Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Prophets by Commiſsion from God, I am made Judge of the Scriptures, and Judge of the light of Chriſt within you, and how will you do? or by what will you try my doctrine and me, ſeeing I am made Judge of the Scriptures, and of your light of Chriſt, and your light of nature, and all that is within you and without you both? it is all to be condemned by me, by which way then can you come to try me, and to make me appear to be a falſe prophet, as you ſay is apparent enough?</p>
            <p>The ſixth and ſeventh things that you upbraid me with, that I ſay there is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of this Doctrine. And that I do preſume under pretence of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of the Spirit, to rob Chriſt of his Office which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath committed unto him as chief Judge ordained of God; with many other ſayings of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne which hath been expreſt in a Letter of mine unto <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> That there is no eternal life to be had now in theſe days, but by faith in the Doctrine of this Commiſsion of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is truth, and many there is that can witneſs the ſame, I mean in thoſe that have heard the ſound of it, and it will be found to be ſo by you <hi>Quakers,</hi> and many hundreds of other Sects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. And as for my ſaying that God hath made me the chief Judge in the world at this day, that is true alſo, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſts having all Judgement put into his hands by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for that is nothing to you what is ſpoken of in Scripture, that will do you no good: for this Chriſt which the Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaks of, is God the Father, and this God hath choſen and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained me to be the chief Judge in ſpiritual and eternal things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Alſo he hath made me Judge of the Scriptures, as I ſaid before, neither have I taken the Office from Chriſt, but he hath given it unto me, and hath inveſted it upon me; neither will he take it away from me, and that you and ſuch as you are ſhall finde to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62519:26"/>
your eternal ſorrow, make as light of it as you will you ſhall not be delivered.</p>
            <p>The latter part of your Letter hath little in it but repeating of Scripture-Texts, and ſome paſſages or words of mine which you do invade againſt me, there is one thing would make one ſmile, and that is this, becauſe it is not written in the Scriptures of truth that I <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> art ordained of God to be the chief Judge in the world in theſe laſt days, will it follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that I am not the chief Judge becauſe my name is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scriptures? If you had lived in the days when Chriſt was upon earth, you would hardly have found his name record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law and the Prophets; nay, it is the more probable that I am ordained the chief Judge, becauſe my name is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in Scripture; for if there had been ſuch a name written in Scriptures that ſhould be the laſt Prophet in the world, many men would have named their ſons <hi>Lodowick Muggleton;</hi> and that is the cauſe there is ſo many <hi>Johns</hi> and <hi>Thomaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Jeremiahs,</hi> with many other Scripture Prophets and Apoſtles names: but there is never a <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> in all the Scriptures, and yet God hath ordained him to be the Judge of <hi>Quakers</hi> and all other deſpiſing ſpirits. And though there be a general Day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, a general day of Execution when men ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the poſſeſsion of eternal happineſs, or eternal miſery, and this may be called the day of Judgement which Chriſt ſhall judge the world with, when as it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Come you bleſſed,</hi> and <hi>Go you curſed:</hi> but the Judgement and Sentence they have in this life by thoſe Prophets, Miniſters and Meſſengers of Chriſt which he hath made Judges for that purpoſe, it is juſt like a Goal-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery. The Judges many times condemns men to die, yet the Execution is not immediately done, but at the day appointed it is: ſo it is with all true Prophets who are made Judges of the ſpiritual and eternal eſtate of mankinde; they have their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this life, and in the day of death it is put in execution by Death; for there ſhall be no more pleading with God, but this will be all that God will ſay in the Reſurrection, <hi>Come you bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and <hi>Go you curſed:</hi> neither ſhall you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others have any other Sentence but what I have paſſed upon you, and when death ſeizeth upon you, then ſhall you enter into the poſſeſsion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62519:26"/>
of it by paſsing through this firſt death, and ſo enter into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death, where you ſhall remain for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place you ſay, that I accuſe the <hi>Quakers</hi> to be of the nature and ſeed of the Serpent, alſo I do ſay that the <hi>Quakers</hi> do preach from the Scriptures and light within, and that devils is caſt out, and much good is done by them.</p>
            <p>And from theſe words of mine you ſay that I confute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict my ſelf, for this <hi>Quaker</hi> would fain prove that becauſe they preach from the Scriptures, and light within, therefore they are ſent of God, for how ſhall they preach, ſaith he, except they be ſent? and by vertue of their preaching, and the power they have received of God, devils are caſt out, and much good is is done by them, and ſuch, ſaith he, are not of the nature and ſeed of the Serpent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> As for you <hi>Quakers</hi> being the nature and ſeed of the Serpent, that is certainly ſo, and can be no other ways, becauſe you are the very influence of <hi>John Robins</hi> ſpiritual witch-craft power upon you, and the very ſpirit of Antichriſt doth run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the bodies of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> for they do all of them deny a perſonal God without them, they do all of them deny alſo the reſurrection of a body, ſo that they are the greateſt fighters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God of any; for they having got Chriſt all within them, they are ſuch a proud, conceited, ſtiff-necked people, that no body can deal with them but this Commiſſion of the Spirit; and this I will ſay to you, that there is never a <hi>Quaker</hi> that is a ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, neither man nor woman that liveth and dyeth in that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that can poſſibly be ſaved, no more then <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> is ſaved, think of your ſelves what you will: and do not you <hi>Quakers</hi> think becauſe you by the letter of the Scriptures, and by the light within you, do caſt out devils, and much good is done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that you are ever the leſs the Serpents ſeed, neither doth that prove that you are ſent of God, but rather the contrary; for the Prieſts of the nation, and all other Sects of Religion doth the ſame things, for the Papiſt Miniſtry by report hath done more wonderous things in that kinde then any <hi>Quaker</hi> ever did, by the laying on of the hands of the <hi>Elders,</hi> and anointing of them with Oyl, and praying over them and ſuch like, they have cured, as they ſay, diſeaſes, and caſt out devils, and other wonderous things,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62519:27"/>
and which I never heard that any <hi>Quaker</hi> ever did: the greateſt things, that ever I have heard the <hi>Quakers</hi> do, is to finde fault with a piece of Ribbon, or Gold-button, or a Bandſtring, and ſuch like, and to poſſeſs themſelves with a melancholly ſpirit of Witch-craft, and ſo fall into Witch-craft fits, to lie humming and groaning, which doth fright the beholders, ſo in ſtead of thoſe merry devils which they had upon the Ranting-ſcore, where all was good lying with their neighbors wife, deſlowering virgins, couzening and cheating, and deſtroying every one in their outward eſtate which did entertain them, and now that devil is caſt out, now they are grown in as much extream on the other ſide, for now they are grown ſo preciſe and exact for apparel and for words, no word muſt be plac'd out of joint, ſo that no man can almoſt tell how to deal with them; and this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy devil hath caſt out the ranting devil, which makes them ſo proud and ſtiff-necked, thinking themſelves that they are better then other people, when as they are worſe, for they are poſſeſt with the ſpirit of Witch-craft, which makes them a two-fold more the children of the devil then they were before, which none can diſcover but this Commiſſion of the Spirit, neither did I ever hear by any which hath heard the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſpeak, that they did ever preach any ſound doctrine, but onely exhort people to hearken to the light within them, which is a very low and eaſie thing for every ordinary underſtanding to comprehend, and that is the cauſe there is ſuch a multitude of men and women fall into it, which if they were ſent of God, there would but few un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their doctrine, nor bear their words; for no <hi>Quaker</hi> need ſuffer any thing for his doctrine, for that is but like other mens, nay, there is not ſo much in their doctrine, as there is in the Prieſts of the nations doctrine, therefore the Quakers are not ſent of God, no more then the Prieſts of the nation, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sect is, for the Prieſts of the nation they preach from the light of the Scriptures, and from the power of the civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> they preach from the letter of the Scriptures, and from the light of Chriſt within; and though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils be caſt out by you both, and much good be done by you both, yet neither of you are ſent of God, becauſe neither of you nor no other is ſent by voice of God without you, ſo that I have not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62519:27"/>
cleared the <hi>Quakers</hi> from being the Serpents ſeed, neither have I confuted my ſelf, neither will my Judgement prove falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you <hi>Quakers,</hi> but you will finde it to as much purpoſe, as if God had ſaid it himſelf, notwithſtanding you call it falſe Judgement, Pride and Preſumption, and error in Judgement, and therefore undone, and holden for nothing by you <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſo forth.</p>
            <p>Now I have given anſwer to as many paſſages in your paper as is neceſſary, I have been ſomething larger then I did intend, but becauſe others may be benefited by it, it may be worth the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor: for had it been no more for others benefit then for yours, I would onely have ſent the ſentence unto you, and no more: but I having read and viewed your paper over with ſerious deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, I finde very little matter or ſubſtance in it, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating of my words: but for that which is your own, the moſt of it is in ſpeaking evil of thoſe truths which you have read out of thoſe four ſheets which was ſent <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> and in that Letter to <hi>Edward Bourn,</hi> which is a clear diſcovery to me that you are the ſeed of the ſerpent, and that you have ſinned the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, for that is a thing which moſt <hi>Quakers</hi> do; for I find in your paper a multitude of blaſphemous ſpeeches againſt this Commiſſion of the Spirit, by calling of it er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, falſe judgment, deluſion, pride, and preſumption, with many more ſuch like expreſſions almoſt at the end of every ſentence, which is enough to damn a thouſand <hi>Quakers,</hi> if they ſhould ſpeak but the fourth part as you have done; therfore in obedience unto my Commiſſion, I do pronounce <hi>Richard Farnſworth,</hi> for this his curſed blaſphemy againſt the holy Spirit that ſent me, curſed and damned, both in ſoul and body, from the preſence of God, elect men Angels to eternity.</p>
            <p>For God hath made me the Judge of the Light of Chriſt within you, and of that infinite Spirit which you call God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out you. For though Chriſt be the true way, yet I am, as <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was, the meſſenger to prepare the way, and to make his paths ſtraight. And though Chriſt be the truth, and the life, yet I am the onely declarer what this truth and life is. And though Chriſt be the door, yet I have the key given me to open the door to life Eternal, and this Commiſſion of the Spirit is that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62519:28"/>
key of <hi>David,</hi> which openeth and no man ſhutteth. And though Chriſt be the true Shepherd which hath laid down his Life for his ſheep, yet I muſt be, as <hi>Peter</hi> was, I muſt feed his ſheep, and feed his Lambs with that green paſture, which is the doctrine of truth, whereby they may ly down in perfect reſt in their minds, and rejoyce in God their Saviour, ſo that they may leap for joy, as the young Lambs do upon the green hills. And though Chriſt be the onely true God, the King of Heaven, yet I am his onely Ambaſſador, ſo that there is no coming to treat with him, but by receiving his Ambaſſador, this Commiſſion of the ſpirit being it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo, How is it poſſible that you <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others, that have deſpiſed the Commiſſion of the Spirit of truth, ſhould eſcape the damnation of Hell?</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Written by</hi> Lodowick Muggelton, <hi>one of the two laſt Witneſſes and Prophets unto the High and Mighty God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="reply_to_pamphlet">
            <head>
               <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi>'s Reply to <hi>Richard Farnſworths</hi> printed Pamphlet.</head>
            <p>I Saw a printed Pamphlet of <hi>Richard Farnſworth,</hi> called, <hi>Truth Aſcended:</hi> Or, <hi>The Anointed and Sealed of God defended,</hi> as a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony as he ſaith, againſt a counterfeit Commiſſion, as he calls it, meaning <hi>Lodowick Muggelton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had thought not to have printed no more, but ſeeing this <hi>Quaker</hi> hath put ſomething in print againſt me, he thinking thereby to make me the more odious unto the world, and to lye the more open to the Magiſtrate, he hath printed this pamphlet againſt me, and becauſe the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſhall not boaſt, as if they had ſet out ſuch a thing that could not be anſwered, I am moved in my mind, to put thoſe Letters of the <hi>Quakers</hi> to me, and my Anſwers to them, with my Anſwer to this printed pamphlet into the publike view, that their deceit may be the more diſcovered
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62519:28"/>
to the world, and that I am not aſhamed to own thoſe Letters which I ſent to them, nor that ſentence and curſe which I have pronounced upon them and others, let the effect be what it will.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> doth ſay, that he is bold in the behalf of the Lord, once again to bear his teſtimony againſt, as he calls it, my pretended Commiſſion, and the Doctrine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I marvel what Lord it is the <hi>Quakers</hi> are bold in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet may blow their Lord away with the breath of his mouth, for they have no other Lord or God, nor Chriſt, but what is within them, for their God nor Chriſt they ſo much talk of, hath never a body nor ſubſtance of his own, as thoſe Letters afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written of mine doth more fully diſcover, wherein the <hi>Quakers</hi> are diſcovered to be led and guided by the ſpirit of Antichriſt, which doth deny God come in the fleſh, that is to ſay, that the fleſh and bone of Jeſus Chriſt, which he ſuffered death in, is not now living in heaven diſtinct of himſelf from man; this I ſay is the <hi>Quakers</hi> faith, and principle, and Antichriſtian, this I know to be true, as will be read in thoſe Letters of mine unto them: and from this body of Jeſus which they deny, have I power to blow <hi>Richard Farnſworths</hi> Lord which he is bold in, away; for they own no other Lord but what is within them, ſo that all <hi>Quakers</hi> in their conceit are Gods, but I ſhall ſay no more of that, but ſhall proceed to anſwer thoſe things which are of moſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and moſt needful in his printed Pamphlet, for the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all people who ſhall come to read or hear it, which is as followeth:</p>
            <p>WHat I have written in a ſheet of paper to <hi>Edward Bourne,</hi> and alſo thoſe four ſheets to <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> which was directed to <hi>Thomas Highfield</hi> at <hi>Notingham,</hi> and I do own to be as true as the Prophets and Apoſtles Writings were to thoſe people in their time, neither ſhall they be delivered from that Sentence which I have declared or pronounced upon them: Alſo I was in ſome hopes that you would have put them Letters, with that which I ſent to you, in print as they were written to them, and you, it would have ſaved me that charge and trouble which now I ſhall be put into; for I will, if I can
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62519:29"/>
get them printed come unto publick view, with your Letters to me without any alteration, but as you have written them to me, ſo that my preſumption, pride, and falſe doctrine, as you call it, and your deceit and Antichriſtian ſpirit may be diſcovered unto the world, that the people may be no more cheated with your hypocritial ſhew of holineſs, which never could have been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by any but by this Commiſſion of the Spirit which God hath given to <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf.</p>
            <p>And whereas you <hi>R. F.</hi> doth ſay, that you are bold on the behalf of the Lord, once again to bear your teſtimony againſt my pretended Commiſſion and the doctrine thereof, and that you ſhall make it appear that it ought not to be entertained by any man or woman upon earth, becauſe, ſay you, it is contrary to truth: And that my Judgement ought by all to be reverſed, undone, and made void, becauſe, ſay you, it is erroneous and falſe; for, ſay you, that I am no choſen Witneſs of the Spirit of Truth; neither have I, ſay you, received any Commiſsion from Chriſt, to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs, as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. M.</hi> Here the Reader may ſee how ſimply he proves that I have no Commiſsion from Chriſt, and that I am no choſen Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. F.</hi> 1. He tells me, that there were choſen Witneſſes of Chriſt to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs: this he proves out of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles</hi> in divers places.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they had a Commiſsion from Chriſt to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs, or that he commanded them to preach to the people. This he proves likewiſe out of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They who were choſen Witneſſes of Chriſt, whom God the Father anointed ſealed and ſent, and had a Commiſsion from the Spirit and Power of Chriſt, to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs, in teſtifying on the behalf of Chriſt, their teſtimony ſtands as an evidence againſt, as you ſay, my pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion and the doctrine thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. M. Reply.</hi> Let any man that knows what belongs to a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Commiſsion, judge whether theſe places of Scripture which you have named, doth prove me a falſe witneſs, and my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62519:29"/>
to be a pretended thing, or no: for I do own and believe that the Prophets under the Law were true witneſſes of Chriſt, that is, they did witneſs and teſtifie unto the people of the Jews that Chriſt the Savior of mankinde was to come, and to be born of a Virgin, this I do faithfully believe. Alſo I do own and believe that the Prophets and Apoſtles were true Witneſſes and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, and that the Apoſtles were choſen Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Chriſt to teſtifie and witneſs that Chriſt the Savior was now born in their time, when they did thus witneſs, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doth abundantly relate. Alſo I do own and believe that Chriſt is ordained to be the Judge of the quick and the dead. Alſo I do own and believe that the Scriptures were ſpoken as Holy men were inſpired, and ſo they may be called, and are owned by me to be, the Word or Words of God. Yet this I ſay by the way, that no man upon the earth at this day, doth know the Scriptures truly, nor can interpret them truly, but us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, becauſe all men in theſe days are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the form and nature of the true God, and the right De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, as I have ſhewed in thoſe Letters to <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> and to <hi>Edward Bournes,</hi> and to your ſelf. Thoſe Letters do open it more at large.</p>
            <p>Again, Do you blinde <hi>Quakers</hi> think that the repeating of Scripture-texts, which were other mens Commiſsions and words, that it will prove me a falſe witneſs, and my Commiſsion to be a pretended thing? then I ſay thoſe Jews which were under the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> might as truly have ſaid as you do by me, that the Apoſtles Commiſsion wat but a pretended thing, and their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which they bore to Chriſt was a falſe witneſs, and ſo they did; therefore they perſecuted them for it, as you would do me if it lay in your power, as it did in theirs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>R. F.</hi> By their Commiſsion they were to preach to the people, and the ſame Commiſsion and the doctrine thereof they were to teſtifie to them that Chriſt was ordained of God to be the Judge both of quick and dead: but thou art not Chriſt to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs, therefore it is evident that thou art not chief Judge ordained of God, though thou preſume to ſay that after death they ſhall never ſee any other God or Judge, but the remembrance of that Sentence which you the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62519:30"/>
pretended Witneſſes of the Spirit did paſs upon them in this life, becauſe thou falſly ſaith, no man knows the Scriptures but thy ſelf, and that no man can truly interpret the Scriptures but thy ſelf, and that no man ought to officiate the Office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger, or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, but ſuch as are appointed by <hi>John Reeve</hi> and thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>Which Aſſertions or Doctrines of thine are falſe, and not true: for this I ſay, that the onely knowledge and right of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting Scriptures belongs not to thy ſelf, but to the Lord Jeſus and his bleſſed Spirit, who is the true Judge, and hath power to open mens underſtandings, and can give them the true knowledge and right underſtanding of Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.32.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Lodowick Muggleton<hi>'s</hi> Reply.</label>
The Reader may ſee the groſs darkneſs of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> here he proves my Commiſſion, as he doth think, to be falſe and a pretended thing, from the letter of the Scripture, as if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles Commiſſion being repeated over ſo many hundred years ſince, would make my Commiſſion falſe, and to be but a pretended thing, when as I do declare that I do not take up my Commiſſion from the letter of the Scriptures, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men do; for that is a pretended Commiſſion which doth counterfeit and pretend to do the ſame things, as they did which had their Commiſſions ſigned and ſealed by the voyce of God himſelf, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> the Prophets and Apoſtles, theſe I do own that they had a Commiſſion from God, but what is this to any <hi>Quaker,</hi> or any other man? doth this prove that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of other mens Commiſſions will make a man a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Ambaſſador of Chriſt? ſurely no, neither will the reading of the Scriptures prove my Commiſſion to be falſe and a pretended thing, as you ſay it is; for I ſaid in thoſe Letters to the <hi>Quakers</hi> that my Commiſſion is as true as the Prophets and Apoſtles Commiſsions were, and of a more higher nature then theirs were, this I own to be true; for my Commiſsion was giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by voyce of words from God as theirs were, therefore it is that I certainly know that God did give a Commiſsion to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets and unto his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Alſo as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were the two firſt that God did chuſe and give a Commiſsion unto, to act forth the Law, which did
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62519:30"/>
ſignifie the water: ſo likewiſe God hath choſen <hi>John Reeve,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggelton</hi> to be his two laſt Witneſſes, and Prophets of the Spirit; ſo that the repeating of the true Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Commiſsions over again now, will never prove me a falſe witneſs nor my Commiſsion to be a pretended thing, for the <hi>Jews,</hi> which were under the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> might, and did as well ſay as you do by me, that the Apoſtles Commiſsion was falſe and a pretended thing, by their repeating of the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: but the repeating of other mens Commiſsions will not make void that which is given by voice of words from God, for that will ſtand for ever, and that you and many more ſhall know to your eternal pain and ſhame, let your pretences be what they will.</p>
            <p>Alſo I do own that the Prophets and Apoſtles of Chriſt did witneſs and teſtifie that Chriſt was ordained of God to be the Judge both of the quick and the dead.</p>
            <p>I alſo do own and believe the ſame thing my ſelf, but what doth this prove therefore that I have no Commiſſion from God to be the chief Judge of <hi>Quakers</hi> and other diſpiſing ſpirits? That doth no ways weaken my power, but rather confirm and make it the more ſtronger, for I do believe Jeſus Chriſt to be the the onely God both God and Man in one perſon, by whom the world was made, and from this Chriſt God Man am I made Judge, and not from the letter of the Scriptures, which were other mens Commiſſions; ſo that I am no Miniſter of the letter, but a Miniſter of the Spirit, and ſo the chief Judge ordained of Chriſt by voice of words, as <hi>Moſes, Elijah, Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> other Prophets and Apoſtles were, ſo that though Chriſt be chief Judge of the quick and the dead, in that he hath power to raiſe mankinde again at the laſt day, and ſo give poſſeſſion of eternal happineſs to the ſeed of Faith, and poſſeſſion of endleſs miſery unto the ſeed of Reaſon, and in this regard Chriſt is chief Judge both of the quick and the dead, yet this doth no ways prove me a falſe Judge but rather the contrary, for all Prophets and Apoſtles which were ordained of God were Judges, and ſome more chief then others, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was a chief Judge, <hi>Elijah,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> and divers others were chief Judges, they being above all other Prophets at that time, therefore chief
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62519:31"/>
Judges in the time of their Commiſſions ſo likewiſe the Apoſtles were all Judges, yet <hi>Peter</hi> was more chief Judge then all the reſt, ſo is it now, <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf being the laſt choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, we are Judges, but while <hi>John Reeve</hi> was living he was chief Judge, but he being fallen a ſleep I am chief Judge, much like unto <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> yet in all this there is no diſ-throning of Chriſt, nor diminiſhing of his honor and power of being the Judge of the quick and the dead. And as for my ſaying, that no man knows the Scriptures, nor can inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the Scriptures truly but my ſelf, that is a ſtanding truth, neither ſhall any man or woman that I have paſſed the Sentence upon be delivered from it; and as for the interpretation of the Scriptures belonging unto the Lord, as you ſay, and not unto my ſelf; to this I ſay, God doth not come down from heaven upon this earth to interpret the Scriptures unto men, but this was always Gods practice to Commiſſionate particular men, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with gifts for that purpoſe, and what interpretations of Scriptures they give, it is owned of God as if he had done it himſelf; therefore the people of the Jews would have <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeak unto them, he being a man like themſelves they could bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hear him then God, becauſe Gods voice was ſo terrible that mortals could not bear it, yet <hi>Moſes</hi> words are owned to be the words of God, as if God had ſpoke them himſelf, and ſo all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles could ſay, <hi>Thus ſayeth the word of the Lord:</hi> ſo that what declaration or interpretation a Meſſenger of God doth give, it may be ſaid it is from God, and ſo ought to be received by man; ſo that Chriſt doth not teach every particular man nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his Spirit, nor by voice of words; but if any man believe him that he is ſent of God, he may be ſaid to be taught of God; ſo that the true and right interpretation of the Scriptures, it lyeth in thoſe men that God hath choſen, anointed, and ſealed for that purpoſe, and men cannot come to the knowledge of God, nor the true meaning of the Scriptures, no other way; ſo that I knowing theſe things to be true, that the interpretation of Scriptures belongs unto Commiſſionated men, and not unto Chriſt himſelf, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> doth vainly imagine.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>R. F.</hi> doth ſay, that the choſen Witneſſes of Chriſt, who had a Commiſſion from his bleſſed Spirit, they were anointed and ſealed of God.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62519:31"/>6. Saith he for the Ambaſſadors who had a Commiſſion to Preach, and were anointed and ſealed of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He ſaith the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt who were anointed and ſealed of God, and had the miniſtration of reconciliation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Ambaſſadors of Chriſt who were anointed and ſealed of God, and had the glorious miniſtration of the Spirit given unto them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He ſaith the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, and choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, who were anointed and ſealed of God, they were workers together with God.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He ſayeth the true Witneſſes of the Spirit and Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of Chriſt, by the Father of Mercies, and God of all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, they were comforted themſelves in all their tribulations that they might be able to comfort them that were in any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by the comfort wherewith they themſelves were comforted of God; for which purpoſe he hath quoted abundance of texts of Scriptures, which would be too tedious to cite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. M. Reply.</hi> Here you that have any true ſaving light in you, you may judge whether this man hath proved me a falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or not: he tells me that the Prophets and Apoſtles of old many hundred years ago before I was born, that they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and ſealed of God for the work of the Miniſtery; that is confeſſed and owned by me, that the Prophets and Apoſtles of old they had a Commiſsion from God to ordain other men for the work of the Miniſtry, but what doth this prove that God hath not given a Commiſsion to <hi>John Reeve</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelton,</hi> becauſe the Prophets and Apoſtles were anointed and ſealed, and had a Commiſsion of God; neither will their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion authorize any <hi>Quakers</hi> nor no other man for the work of the Miniſtry; but when the Prophets and Apoſtles were living, they had power to authorize any man which they did diſcern fit for it, but the reading of their Commiſsion now they are dead, will not impower a man to be a Miniſter or Meſſenger of Chriſt, yet this is the courſe that you <hi>Quakers</hi> and moſt men in the world doth take to prove a live mans Commiſsion to be falſe, by a dead mans Commiſſion; but you will finde it to the contrary in the end.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62519:32"/>Again though the Prophets and Apoſtles were anointed and ſealed of God for that great work, will it follow therefore that you <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe you read their writings, that you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and ſealed of God for the work of the Miniſtry? ſurely no, neither will it follow, becauſe they were true Witneſſes of Chriſt, therefore I muſt needs be falſe: For this I ſay, that my Commiſſion is from the ſame God as theirs was and is as true as theirs was, neither have I my Commiſsion from them, but from God himſelf as they had, ſo that it will prove a vain conceit of you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others that are under the ſentence of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of the ſpirit, to tell me that they were, that is, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles were anointed and ſealed of God; what is that to you what they were? their being true Witneſſes of Chriſt, will never a whit diminiſh or weaken that power and authority which God hath given me, but confirm and ſtrengthen it the more, in that I know that they had the like power in their time, according to the nature of their Commiſsion, as I have: And now I certainly know that they were true, and what their their power was, in that I know my ſelf to be true, and what my power is now, ſo that I cannot be deceived as you <hi>Quakers</hi> are with other mens Commiſſions that are dead, you not knowing the extent of their Commiſsions, nor when they began, nor when they did end; and your ignorance of thoſe things makes you fight with the dead letter againſt a living Spirit, juſt as if a man ſhould fight with the ſheath againſt him that hath a two-edged Sword in his hand, ſo do you <hi>Quakers</hi> with me.</p>
            <p>And as for my fleeing from <hi>Cheſterfield</hi> to <hi>Backwel</hi> for fear of a few ſtripes, or a whipping, when the ſame was but threatened againſt me, this is utterly falſe; for I did not know that any ſuch thing was threatned againſt me, neither was I ever at <hi>Backwel</hi> in my life to my knowledge; neither did it lye in the power of the Magiſtrates in that Countrey to do any ſuch thing, in caſe they had catcht me at that time: I ſay it was more than their Law would bear them out to do: but however if I had fled for fear of the Devils malice, I did no more then other Prophets and Apoſtles which were Ambaſſadors of Chriſt before me, they did the ſame: as <hi>Eliah</hi> fled from <hi>Jezabel,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> fled for fear of perſecution: and Chriſt gave advice to his diſciples, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62519:32"/>
when they were perſecuted in one City, to flee into another, ſo that would have been no new thing, neither ſhould I have been e're the more a falſe Witneſs or Ambaſſador of Chriſt if I had fled for fear of a whipping.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſay that I was threatned for my falſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Doctrine, as you call it, ſaying it was reviling, curſing, and damning: As for curſing and damning, I do own that I did paſs the Sentence of eternal damnation upon ſome <hi>Quakers</hi> and others, that was but according to the tenor of my Commiſsion from Chriſt, and I am very well ſatisfied in ſo doing: but as for my reviling of any man or woman I never did, it was alwayes contrary to my natural temper before I knew what a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was, to revile any man or woman, much leſs now, that I think the Prieſt of <hi>Cheſterfield</hi> will witneſs, that when I was catcht and brought before the Mayor thereof, and examined by the Prieſt, I gave him nor no other man there, no reviling ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: but as I am a Prophet and a Witneſs of the Spirit, diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that the Prieſt was of the ſeed of the ſerpent, and of a perſecuting ſpirit, which would have took away my life, if it had layen in his power, or in the power of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> he would have done it, though I never had any prejudice, nor no ſpeech with the man in my life before, yet his envy and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice was ſo great to me; for which I did paſs the Sentence of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal damnation upon him, but no ways reviling, but did give him civil reſpect as a Prieſt of the Nation, which I think he will witneſs, notwithſtanding his malice and envy was great to me which did him no wrong, nor no man elſe in that town, yet he cauſed me to be ſent unto <hi>Derby</hi> Goal, where I did remain until the Aſſizes; ſo that the malice of men hath been exerciſed upon me as much as lieth in their power to do, and it is onely upon this account, they cannot endure that God ſhould give power to a man like themſelves, to bleſs and curſe to eternity.</p>
            <p>Neither do I curſe any until he judge me firſt, much leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile any: you may as well ſay that a Judge when he paſſeth Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon a malefactor to be hanged for the breach of ſuch a law, that is capable of death, you may as well ſay that this Judge doth revile, curſe, and condemn the man that hath broke the law, when as the Judge can do no otherwiſe, but according to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62519:33"/>
the tennor of his Commiſsion which he is authorized by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the King: ſo that every Judge is made a ſavour of life and death; for the one he condemns to die according to the law, and the other he doth acquit and ſet free, and is this any leſs then a temporal bleſsing and curſing, and no reviling at all? Even ſo it is with me, I being one of Gods choſen Witneſſes and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors by vertue of his Commiſson given unto <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf, I am made Judge of men and womens ſpiritual and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal eſtate, what ſhall become of them after death, yet this I would have the reader to underſtand, that though a Judge of the Land be Judge of many Countries and Shires, yet his power is ſeen moſt in thoſe that he doth acquit or condemn; ſo is it with me, my power is moſt ſeen in thoſe that receive and believe me, and ſo are bleſſed to eternity, and in thoſe that deſpiſe and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute me, in that they are curſed and damned to eternity; for I never bleſs none but thoſe that truly believe it, neither do I curſe any but thoſe that deſpiſe or perſecute me upon that account: but all that doth neither receive it nor deſpiſe it, I let them alone and meddle not with them, but leave them to ſtand or fall as the two ſeeds within them ſhall uphold them, or let them fall. And as for your ſaying that I have reviled, curſed, and damned the beloved people of God, meaning you <hi>Quakers:</hi> So that I ſay I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did curſe any of them till ſuch time as they did Judge or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe my Commiſsion firſt; for I never do judge firſt, ſo that I am certain that moſt part of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are the ſeed of the ſerpent, and not the beloved of God: ſo that thoſe <hi>Quakers</hi> which I have curſed ſhall not eſcape, they being the ſeed of the ſerpent, and have deſpiſed to be taught any other way but by the light within them. But I have opened that more clear in thoſe Letters to <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi> and to <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> himſelf, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall ſay no more in that point.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſs by thoſe ten particulars repeated by <hi>R. F.</hi> to prove me not a choſen Witneſs of the Spirit, and ſhall come to that which is of more concernment for the reader to know, that is, that God hath choſen me now in theſe laſt days to be an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador and Witneſs of the Spirit, and ſo chief Judge in the world concerning the ſpiritual and eternal eſtate of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men after death, and that I do go by as certain a rule, as the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62519:33"/>
Judges of the Land do when they give Judgement according to Law, as may be ſeen aforeſaid in the Letters to the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here <hi>R.F.</hi> would ſeem to prove me a liar: Firſt, becauſe ſaith he, thou art both judge, accuſer, and witneſs thy ſelf, and ſaith that I do condemn and give judgement at my will and pleaſure contrary to truth. And he further ſaith, that I do not go in ſo doing by ſo certain a rule as the Judges of the Land do. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He ſaith, that I go not by ſo certain a rule when I paſs the Sentence of death and damnation upon the ſouls and bodies of men, as the Judges of the Land doth; for which purpoſe he doth quote Judge <hi>Cook</hi> upon the confirmation of the Charters of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> who ſayeth this cauſe is worthy to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Letters of gold, now what that clauſe is; would be too tedious to write: but the ſum of all is, that the Judges of the Land have certain outward known Laws, as a rule of direction to guide and lead them to judgement when they give it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law: but, ſaith he, thou <hi>Lodowick,</hi> haſt no certain out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward known Laws either of God or the land, as rule of direction, and ſo forth. Likewiſe he quoted many places of Scriptures, and ſome out of the civil Law, ſome out of <hi>Edw.</hi> third, and <hi>Cooks Inſt.</hi> and with the Proverbs of <hi>Solomon:</hi> he hath paid me with <hi>Solomons</hi> words, and ſo bids me take notice of that which I do take great notice: for I ſee by that, that the Proverbs of <hi>Solomon</hi> is as good Scripture to the <hi>Quakers</hi> as any, and how well the <hi>Quakers</hi> knows the Scriptures, I am never a whit deceived in them people, for they ſeem to have the greateſt light, but are the darkeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all in the knowledge of the Scriptures, and in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scriptures; according to the common ſenſe the Prieſts of the Nation doth go far beyond them, for the <hi>Quakers</hi> are ſo choaked up with hearkening to the light of Chriſt within them, that they deſpiſe the body or perſon of Chriſt without them, but I have diſcovered their Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chriſt ſpirit more large in other Letters unto them, ſo that I ſhall ſay the leſs here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. M. Reply.</hi> The great thing to be known is, how I will do to prove my ſelfe to be the chief Judge in ſpiritual matters, and that I do go by as certain a rule as the Judges of the Land do, when as they give Judgement according to Law, ſeeing he hath brought ſo many places of Scripture, and the Proverbs of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62519:34"/>
and Acts of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and Judge <hi>Cooks</hi> Judgement of the Law, all to prove me a falſe Judge, and that I do not go in my ſentence by any known Law, either of God nor the Land, ſo that if this be anſwered, moſt part of his Pamphlet will be anſwered, For it doth conſiſt moſt part of it upon this thing; therefore I ſhall give anſwer to it, that others may be the better informed in themſelves, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugh I am ſatisfied in it as to my ſelf, yet this I do ingeniouſly confeſs, that I never did pretend the knowledge of the Civil Laws of the Land, neither do I. Now all the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that I profeſs to know of them, is to yeild obedience unto them, in doing of them, or elſe to ſuffer the penalty or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, this is the greateſt knowledge I have of them; for if my innocency nor mony will not deliver me, I muſt and will ſuffer under it; but ſince God hath choſen <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf to be his laſt Witneſſes of the Spirit, I know the better true power of a Judge; For as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were the two firſt choſen Witneſſes of God, ſo likewiſe <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf are the two laſt that God will ever chuſe by voice of words to the hearing of the ear: and as <hi>Aaron</hi> was given to be <hi>Moſes</hi> mouth, ſo <hi>Lodowick Muggelton</hi> was given to be <hi>John Reeve</hi> mouth theſe things cannot be known but by faith, neither can any man tell that God choſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> but by faith. But if it be objected, that <hi>Moſes</hi> did miracles: To that I anſwer, that there is as much need of faith to believe that as the other, for what cannot be ſeen muſt be believed: So believing that God ſpake to <hi>John Reeve,</hi> and that God gave unto <hi>John Reeve</hi> a Commiſſion by voice from Heaven by verbal words to the hearing of the ear three mornings together, and that I was given to be his mouth, and by his voice did I receive my Commiſſion, whereby I am impowered to be a Meſſenger and Ambaſſador for the great God the Man Chriſt Jeſus, which is both God and Man, who hath choſen me to be at this day chief Judge, and hath given me a Commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion ſo to be, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in his time, meaning himſelf, and the reſt of his Apoſtles: <hi>We,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are Ambaſſadors in Chriſts ſtead beſeeching you to be reconciled,</hi> and the like: So ſay I, that I am an Ambaſſador in Chriſts ſtead, to bleſs them that are reconcil'd unto the true faith in Chriſt, and to curſe and damn thoſe that deſpiſeth and ſpeaketh evil of them whom God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62519:34"/>
hath ſent; So that God hath made me chief Judge now to give ſentence upon men and womens ſpiritual and eternal eſtate, ſo that I ſhall unfold as ſhort as I can, how I may be ſaid to be the chief Judge, and that I do go by as certain a rule as the Judges of the Land do when they give Judgement according to Law. Theſe two things I ſhall unfold a little more clear then in thoſe Letters aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that I am chief Judge in ſpiritual matters, I prove thus: Becauſe I do believe and certainly know by the revelation of Faith, that God did ſpeak to <hi>John Reeve</hi> three mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtinct words and ſentences to the hearing of the ear, in the year 1651. <hi>February</hi> the third, fourth, and fift, and gave him a Commiſsion as he did <hi>Moſes.</hi> And <hi>Aaron</hi> was given to be <hi>Moſes</hi> his mouth, ſo was <hi>Lodowick Muggelton</hi> given to be <hi>John Reeve</hi> mouth, ſo that <hi>John Reeve</hi> being the chief while he was living, but ſince the burthen or Commiſſion of the Lord hath been laid upon me; and as <hi>Eliſha</hi> had a double portion of <hi>Eliahs</hi> Spirit; ſo have I had a double portion of Revelation of the Spirit in opening the Scriptures ſince <hi>John Reeve</hi> departed this life. Alſo God ſaid, that he had choſen <hi>John Reeve</hi> his laſt Meſſenger, and that he had given him <hi>Lodowick Muggelton</hi> to be his mouth, and the next words following, that he had put the two edged-ſword of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into his mouth, to pronounce Bleſsing and Curſing to eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with many other words which are in publike, therefore I ſhall ſay no more of them here, ſo that <hi>John Reeve</hi> being dead, I muſt needs be chief Judge in theſe dayes, neither will God Commiſsionate any more after me to the worlds end, becauſe he did ſay that he had choſen us his laſt. Now I being his laſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Meſſenger, I muſt needs be chief Judge of ſpiritual matters concerning men and womens eternal eſtate, and what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them after death, if theſe things cannot be believed by you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others, I cannot help that, neither doth this power which God hath given me any ways diſhonor or diſthrone Chriſt of his Office of being the Judge of the Quick and the Dead; for God doth do much like unto an Earthly King, for though a King be the chief Judge of thoſe Kingdoms which he is King of, yet he doth Commiſsionate ſome particular man to be chief Judge, to be in his ſtead: though the King doth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionate
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62519:35"/>
many more Judges, yet there is but one particular in every Kingdom which is called <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice of England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> theſe being three diſtinct Kingdoms, they have three diſtinct particular perſons, which are called <hi>Chief Judges,</hi> and they are ſo by Commiſsion from the King, beſides all other Judges; yet you ſee that the King though he be Chief Judge of all his Kingdoms, yet he ſeldom or never acts in Judgement himſelf, but doth leave it to thoſe which he hath Commiſsionated for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>So is it with the God of Heaven, though Chriſt which is God and Man, be King of heaven and chief Judge both in Heaven and in Earth in ſpiritual and eternal matters, yet he by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth choſe ſome particular perſon to be chief judge in ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual things, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was choſen chief Judge, and <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and divers other Prophets which did govern <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were chief Judges in the worſhip of God at that time, as there muſt alſo be one particular man that muſt be High-prieſt, ſo likewiſe <hi>Peter</hi> was the chief Apoſtle, and ſo chief Judge, ſo that ſome particular man muſt be chief in all places of truſt, whether it be under a earthly King, or under the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yet no diſhonor nor diſ-throning either of them both, ſo the God and King of heaven having choſen <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf, he hath Commiſsionated me to be his Meſſenger, Miniſter, or Ambaſſador in his ſtead, to ſet life and death before men, even as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to the people of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and as men and women do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, they ſhall have life eternal abiding in them, and ſome can witneſs it at this day, and as men and women doth deſpiſe the Doctrine of Truth declared by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, they have the ſentence and ſeal of eternal death abiding in them, and many can witneſs that in themſelves, but that they will not; yet ſome few to my knowledge hath been forc'd to do it thorough the terror of ſoul: but however it is not the fewneſs of them that do receive it, nor the multitude of them that deſpiſe it, doth make me queſtion e're the more the truth of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and though Chriſt be the King of heaven, and the Judge of the quick and the dead at the laſt day, and ſo he is the chief Judge, in that he can raiſe men and women again, and give the poſſeſſion both of eternal happineſs and eternal miſery, according
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62519:35"/>
to that ſentence which the Prophets and Apoſtles, and we the Witneſſes of the Spirit did paſs upon them in this life, ſo that we ſee that God hath made chief Jugdes in ſpiritual matters, we do no ways diſ-throne Chriſt of his Office, no more then the chief Judge of <hi>England</hi> doth diſ-throne the King, in that his Commiſſion from the King will bear him out, he judging accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tenor of his Commiſſion; ſo is it with me, God having made me chief judge of mens ſpiritual and eternal eſtate, what will become of them after death, and I going and judging ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tennor of my Commiſſion, I do no ways diſhonor my King, but honor him, in that I am faithful to that truſt which God hath intruſted me with, and I am very well ſatisfied in the performance of it, yet this I would have the reader to know, though I do own my ſelf the chief judge in ſpiritual matters, yet this I ſay that every true believer of this Commiſſion is a judge as well as I my ſelf, and may upon occaſions when they meet with deſpiſing ſpirits, curſe them to eternity, if their ſaith be ſtrong enough to bear them up; ſo that they do not doubt. For if any ſhall paſs the ſentence upon another, and doubt, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of that ſentence will return back again to themſelves: this I have ſeen in ſome believers of this Commiſſion of the Spirit, ſome again of the believers have been ſo ſtrong in their faith, that the ſentence which they have paſſed upon deſpiſing ſpirits, it hath had as great effect upon them it was paſſed upon, as mine hath, and rather greater, ſo that every believer of this Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whoſe faith is ſtrong is a judge as well as I, though not chief judge: but if peoples faith be weak and not ſtrong enough to bear them out in it, I do not tie them to any ſuch thing, but I could wiſh they were all ſo ſtrong that the devils might be met with every where, where the knowledge of this Commiſſion of the Spirit is known and believed. And as the King of earth hath many Judges in his Kingdom, yet but one chief Judge, in l ke manner is it with God the King of Heaven, he hath many Judges of deſpiſing ſpirits in ſpiritual and eternal things, yet but one chief judge: and as the Apoſtles were chief Judges in their time, yet the believers of them were ſaints and ſo judges, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaid, <hi>that the ſaints ſhould judge the earth; nay,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, know you not that we ſhall judge Angels?</hi> What is that? That is,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62519:36"/>
you that are believers of our Goſpel, you ſhall be made by the power of faith to judge wiſe and prudent Angel-like men, in the wiſdom of reaſon which came from the fallen angels ſeed and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, indued with piercing, rational God-like wiſdom, therefore called Angels; theſe are thoſe Angels which the Saints in <hi>Pauls</hi> time ſhould judge: ſo is it now with me, I being chief judge in theſe laſt days, I have judged many wiſe Luciferian Angel-like ſpirits within this twelve years, and ſo hath ſome of the believers in this time judged many of theſe Angels, they may be called Angels, becauſe they are of the ſerpent Angels ſeed, and hath the higheſt wiſdom of Reaſon in them which their fallen eſtate will afford, but the weak and ſimple ſeed of faith muſt be their judges, ſo that it may be clear to the reader that underſtands, that all true believers of this Commiſſion of the Spirit are judges of men and womens ſpiritual and eternal eſtate, what ſhal become of them after death, yet none to be chief judge but my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing is to ſhew that I do go by as certain a rule as the Judges of the Land do, when as they give judgement according to Law: To this I ſay that the Judges of the Land they have a Commiſſion firſt from the King to be Judges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They have the Book of the Law to be their guides.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They muſt be men ſuppoſed to know the Law.</p>
            <p n="4">4. According to the known Law the Judge giveth ſentence and judgement either to acquit or condemn by the Law.</p>
            <p>So is it with me: Firſt, God hath given me a Commiſſion to be chief judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He hath given me the Book of the Law.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He hath given me to know the Law.</p>
            <p n="4">4. According to the known law I do give ſentence and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of bleſſing or curſing to eternity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I have a Commiſſion from God to be chief judge, that I have proved before, if it cannot be believed I cannot help that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That God hath given the Book of the Law which is the Scriptures into my hand, is as certainly true alſo; for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are given into my hands, as the Prieſts office was given unto the hands of <hi>Aaron,</hi> yet every man that read the Scriptures doth think to finde eternal life in them, as Chriſt ſaid to the Jews, and as you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others doth now a days;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62519:36"/>
but thinking will not ſerve turn, for all moſt all the world hath no other aſſurance of eternal life but thinking: but it is knowledge and faith in the true God that gives certain aſſurance of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, which I know no <hi>Quaker</hi> hath, or can have in that eſtate and principle which they hold; for they deny that fleſh and bone of Chriſt which ſuffered death to be now living above the Stars in that Heaven; but I have opened that more large in thoſe Letters to the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God hath given me to know the Law, that is, to know the Book of the Scriptures; and that he hath given me more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Scriptures than all the men in the world at this day: this I know to be truth, and ſome others can witneſs it, neither can any man interpret the Scriptures truly but my ſelf and thoſe that have it from me, becauſe no man doth know the true foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations which the Book of the Scriptures doth ſtand upon, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the true God, and the right Devil.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And according to the known Law of the Scriptures, I do give Sentence and judgement of bleſſing and curſing to eternity.</p>
            <p>Thus far I do proceed like unto the Judges of the Land, but now as for Juries, and witneſſes, and accuſers, the Judges of the Civil Law and I ſhall differ ſomething, but not much, becauſe Juries and Judges are ſo bound together by the Civil Laws of the Land, that one in many caſes can do nothing without the other, ſo that many times there is a great deal of hurt done as well as good, becauſe the power lyeth in them both; for many times when Judges would do right according to Law, yet the Iury doth prevent him, and ſo tyeth his hands: likewiſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Iury is willing to ſhew mercy, and do right, and the Judge will not, having ſome prejudice againſt that party, and doth over-power the Jury with his authority and knowledge in the Law, ſo that Judgement is turned backward ſometimes becauſe the Law lyeth between two, the Judge and the Jury; which if it did lye always in one, then there would be always either true Juſtice done, or injuſtice alwayes done theſe things ſome can experience which have been accuſtomed to the Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Judges of the Civil Law, can do nothing except there be Witneſſes or Accuſers face to face, the cauſe of that is, becauſe the Laws of the Land are grounded upon Reaſon,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62519:37"/>
and the Judges of the Land are the interpreters of the Law of reaſon, ſo that Reaſons kingdom being in this viſible world, it muſt proceed in the way of reaſon, by the Law of reaſon, which is the Law of the Land, for the Law of the Land can lay hold of nothing but what is a viſible breach of the Law; therefore the Judge muſt have a viſible Witneſs or Accuſer face to face, elſe be can give no Judgement upon the matter, yet there is ſome caſes in Law that men are ſued at the Law, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Law at a diſtance, the party ſued, not being face to face, nor knowes of it until that he be condemned; this ſome can experience, yet this I ſay the Judes of the Land doth go the beſt way in having Iuries and Witneſſes that reaſon could find out, and for my part I do approve of their way very well, but whom God doth make judges, they muſt go a neerer way to work; for you may read that thoſe judges which God did ordain in ſpiritual matters, they did not call for Juries and Witneſſes as the Judges of the Land do: what Jury did <hi>Moſes</hi> call for to plague the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their Idolatry? And what Jury did <hi>Elijah</hi> call for when he called for fire from Heaven to deſtroy thoſe two Captains and their fifties? What Jury did <hi>Eliſha</hi> call for when he curſed thoſe forty two children, and cauſed them to be ſlain by two She-bears? What Jury did <hi>Peter</hi> call for when he ſtrake <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Saphirah</hi> his wife dead with a word ſpeaking? with many more things which the Prophets and Apoſtles which were Judges of ſpiritual matters have done without any Juries or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and yet they have gone by as certain a rule as the Iudges of the Land do when they give judgement according to Law: ſo that I do know how to proceed in Iudgement according to the tenor of my Commiſsion, as the Prophets and Apoſtles did in theirs, and as the Iudges of the Land do in their Commiſſion of the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>But to give little further ſatisfaction to the Reader, I ſhall ſhew why I do condemn men and women at a diſtance, and yet ſomething agreeable to the way of the Law of the Land: Firſt thoſe that are condemned by me at a diſtance, there is ſome of this Faith that hath heard them ſpeak wicked ſpeeches againſt me, and the doctrine declared by this Commiſsion of the Spirit, and have given me intelligence of it, and ſo upon their witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62519:37"/>
the ſame I have ſent the ſentence unto them, ſo that if the witneſs that informed me did not witneſs truth, then that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which I have paſſed upon them ſhall be of no value, which is better judgement in ſome kinde then the Judges of the Land doth give, for if Witneſſes be falſe and ſwear falſly, the Judges of the Land do many times condemn the innocent meerly tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row falſe Witneſs, therefore in that regard my judgement and ſentence is more certain then the Judges of the Civil Law is, in regard I never condemn the innocent thorow falſe witneſs, for I ſeldom or never do ſend the ſentence to any, though their wicked ſpeeches be witneſſed unto me by one that is not in this faith, though they may ſpeak truth in that thing as well as others that are of the ſame faith with me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I never do paſs ſentence on any at a diſtance, except I have ſome Writing from their own hands, as I have had from you <hi>Quakers,</hi> and your Hand-writing is as good a Jury and witneſs to me, as the Iudges of the Land can have, for what jury or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs can be required more then a mans own hand Writing? Others again have blaſphemed againſt the holy Spirit that ſent me in my hearing, ſo that there doth need no jury, nor wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, nor accuſers, but their own words, for by them ſhall they be condemned or juſtified: for you ſee that men are put to death for ſpeaking treaſon againſt the King, as well as for acting Treaſon, ſo is it with God; for words of blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt, is a ſin that God will never fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>give, neither in this world nor in the world to come, yet we read in Scripture that all manner of other ſins ſhall be forgiven unto men, but not that ſin, and this I ſay there is more <hi>Quakers</hi> guilty of that ſin then any other Sect whatſoever, and for that very ſin have I paſſed the ſentence of eternal death upon ſo many of them: for God hath g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven me a diſcerning to know when a man doth commit that ſin, I being one of the Witneſſes of the Spirit, and ſo judge of them that I know doth commit it, I do give judgement and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of eternal damnation upon them, ſo that I am neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer nor witneſs in thoſe that are condemned at a diſtance, but their own writings or their own words ſhall be a witneſs and an accuſer againſt them: for I do accuſe no man of ſin, but gives judgement upon them for their ſin: and if you call the ſentence
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62519:38"/>
that I paſs upon them to be an accuſation and a witneſs againſt them, then indeed in that ſenſe I am both judge, accuſer, and witneſs my ſelf; but theſe things afore-mentioned being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, will prove that I do go by as certain a rule when I paſs ſentence of eternal damnation upon the bodies and ſouls of men and women, as the Iudges of the Land do, when they give judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to Law; and as the Charters and Liberties of <hi>England</hi> are worthy to be written in letters of gold as Judge <hi>Cock</hi> doth ſay, becauſe of the excellency and juſtneſs of them, I ſay ſo too, for I always loved legal juſtice among men: ſo I ſay likewiſe that thoſe Letters which I have ſent to you <hi>Quakers</hi> are worthy to be written in Letters of gold, alſo that they might indure in the memory of men and women to the worlds end, for I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they will indure in your memory to eternity.</p>
            <p>Yet in all this I do neither own my ſelf a King, nor God, not Chriſt, nor the Holy Ghoſt, nor any of thoſe titles do I take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, but this I do own my ſelf to be one of the two laſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Witneſſes of the Spirit, or Meſſenger, Miniſter, or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, this I do own my ſelf to be, and by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Commiſſion I received from Chriſt I am made chief Judge in ſpiritual matters in all thoſe that doth either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my Doctrin, or deſpiſe it: But as for others that doth neither receive it, nor deſpiſe it, nor hear of it, I Judge them not, but leave them as God ſhall find them at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>R. F.</hi> doth ſay, that God hath reſerved a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning power in the Eternal God-head and a puniſhing power to correct and puniſh me, and ſuch as I am: alſo he ſaith, wouldſt thou make the Eternal Power and God-head inferior to the Kings of the Earth? Doth not, ſaith he, the Kings of the Earth reſerve a pardoning and puniſhing power in themſelves, beſides what they give to their Judges by their Commiſſion? So in his concluſion of that matter, he doth affirm that there is a puniſhing power reſerved in the Eternal God-head, and doth therewith remain to puniſh the rebellious, and obſtinate, and preſumptuous, ſuch, ſaith he, as I am, or as may be read <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. with many more places of Scriptures which would be tedious to cite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. M. Reply.</hi> That there is reſerved a pardoning power and a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62519:38"/>
puniſhing power in the Eternal God-head, that I do own and believe, but the pardoning power in the God-head doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to thoſe that are condemned by thoſe which God hath made Iudges, why? becauſe thoſe Iudges that God doth make in ſpiritual and Eternal things, they go by a certain rule: thoſe Iudges doth either diſcern men and women to be the abſolute ſeed of the Serpent, or elſe that they have ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt: theſe two things are infallible rules for Gods Iudges to go by, for will any one think that when <hi>Peter</hi> retained any mans ſins, that God would forgive that mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h's ſins afterwards? ſurely no: ſo ſay I, you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others that are condemned by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, you will not be pardoned of God, becauſe moſt of you have ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt eſpecially you that have written to me in calling the Doctrin and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of us the Witneſſes of the Spirit whom God hath choſen, anointed and ſealed, to reveal the whole councel of God, in that he became fleſh, which is the greateſt miſterie, in that we the Witneſſes of the Spirit are ſo far honoured of God as to be the finiſhers of it as <hi>John, Revelation,</hi> the 10, doth ſpeak of: I ſay you <hi>Quakers</hi> have deſpiſed it more then all other men, by calling this Doctrin blaſphemy, error, lies, and deceit, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wicked ſpeeches which could not have been ſpoken but by the ſeed of the Serpent; therefore I am no ways deceived in ſaying that thoſe people called <hi>Quakers</hi> that the moſt part of them are of the ſeed of the Serpent, and not the beloved of God as you ſay, ſo that they and others that I have paſſed the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon will not eſcapet though their be a pardoning pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the God-head, yet none of thoſe which I have pronounced ſentence upon, ſhall partake of it for thoſe reaſons aforeſaid: For though there be a power in the God-head to do what he will, yet when he hath given his word he will not go back from it, becauſe he cannot ly: So that it is not your repeating what power the Prophets and Apoſtles of old had, nor the multitude of Scriptures which you have rehearſed, that will ſtand you in any ſteed, nor deliver you from that ſentence which I have paſſed upon you, yet in all this I do not make the Eternal God-head inferiour to the Kings of the earth. I do alſo acknowledge that the Kings of the earth reſerve a pardoning power in themſelves, beſides what they give to their Iudges: But this I
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62519:39"/>
muſt ſay to you that it is very ſeldom known that an earthly King hath any pardoning power in himſelf for ſuch traitors that act treaſon againſt the Kings perſon, this I ſuppoſe all mens experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will witneſs, ſo that there is ſome crimes that earthly Kings have no pardoning power for in themſelves: ſo is it with you <hi>Quakers,</hi> you have committed ſuch a ſin even againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſo that there is no pardon in God himſelf not for you, no more then there is for <hi>Cain</hi> that ſlew <hi>Abel,</hi> nor <hi>Judas</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed Chriſt: if theſe be ſaved, then you ſhall, and remember you were told ſo by the laſt true Prophet. But if earthly Kings do pardon any traitor, it is becauſe ſome other perſons in great power doth petition or intercede to the King for him, and ſo perhaps the King for ſome ends beſt known to himſelf, may ſave his life, but keep him in priſon all days of his life, ſo that this can not properly be called a pardoning power, except he freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him, and raiſe him up to the ſame honor which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but you <hi>Quakers</hi> have no ſuch friend to intercede for you to the King of Heaven, now you are condemned by his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger; for Chriſt will not intercede for you, for you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him before men, in that you deny that fleſh and bone which he ſuffered death in, and roſe again in the ſame fleſh and bone, and aſcended up into heaven, and doth now remain there in that ſame body, onely it is ſpiritualized and glorified body, yet a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: this I ſay, you <hi>Quakers</hi> doth deny, whatſoever you may prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and talk of a Chriſt, yet you own no Chriſt but what is within you, this I know to be true, elſe I ſhould not be ſo j alous againſt thoſe people more then others, but for this very thing that Chriſt will never intercede for pardon for you <hi>Quakers</hi> that are condemned by me; yet this I ſhall ſay if it will pleaſe you, that if I be a falſe prophet and witneſs as you ſay I am, then I ſay that curſe which I have paſſed upon you and many others; I ſay let it be all upon me, and you ſhall all go free: but if I be true as I know I am, there is no poſſibility for you nor others to eſcape. I can ſay no more in this thing, but ſhall leave it to Chriſt the Judge of the quick and the dead, to give me my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward according as I have been faithful in the Commiſſion which he hath put upon me.</p>
            <p>Againe, it is not with earthly kings as it is with the King of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62519:39"/>
Heaven, for many times earthly kings have their pardoning power and their Condemning power which they have in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves taken away from them, and ſo doth ſtand in need of pardon themſelves, and ſo all thoſe Iudges which had their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions from the king is worth nothing, becauſe another power hath overcome him, and hath took it by the power of the ſword; ſo that earthly kings doth ſometimes ſtand in need of pardon and mercy themſelves: for an earthly power doth ſtand no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then till a ſtronger then he doth overcome him, as may be read concerning the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and others which fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as <hi>Saul</hi> againſt King <hi>Agag,</hi> and <hi>Jehu</hi> againſt the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and divers others which might be named: and ſo in <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmany</hi> and many places of Chriſtendom, and here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath not the pardoning and condemnidg power been rent out of the Kings hands? and ſo all thoſe Iudges which had their Commiſsions from him, are put out of their places of power, and ſo their Commiſsion is made void and of none effect? This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in theſe our days hath ſhewed the truth of it, but that Commiſsion which is given of God the King of Heaven, cannot be made void, neither can that man which God hath made Iudge of ſpiritual and eternal matters, I ſay that mans Commiſsion cannot be taken away by any but by God himſelf: and ſeeing that no power can conquer or overcome God the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to diſ-throne him, becauſe he is from everlaſting to everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and look what thoſe Iudges that God hath choſen, anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſealed for that purpoſe, their Sentence is for everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and to eternity, as God himſelf is: For as an earthly Kings power doth laſt no longer than his life, and not always ſo long, ſo God being for ever to eternity, ſo will thoſe his commiſsion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Iudges their Sentence be everlaſting and eternal a ſo; ſo that thoſe Iudge; which God hath commiſsionated, even we the Witneſſes of the Spirit, do go by a more certain rule than the Iudges of the land do, when they give Iudgement according to Law; neither can that ſentence which I have paſſed upon you <hi>Quakers</hi> and others be revoked, not as the Iudges of the Lands ſentence may through many tricks and quibbles in the Law: but no trick nor quibble in the repeating of Scripture-texts as you have done, ſhall deliver you, becauſe I know the Law of the Scriptures, as well as the Iudges of the Land do the Civil Law;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62519:40"/>
and though they may through Iuries and falſe witneſſes give wrong ſentence ſometimes, it is not ſo with me, for I do walk by a more infallible rule than they do, when I paſs ſentence upon men and women; for it is not Iuries nor falſe witneſſes that can turn, or make me give judgement contrary to truth, becauſe I received my power and authority from the God of Truth; and let men rage, revile, perſecute, and do what they can, they will not be delivered from that Judgement that I have paſſed upon them, and if their perſecution ſhould extend unto death, it will but make the fire of hell to burn the more hotter in their ſouls to eternity.</p>
            <p>In the latter part of your Pamphlet you ſpake ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the two Witneſſes; for, ſay you, if <hi>John Reeve</hi> and thy ſelf were Joint-Commiſſioners, and had your pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion not ſeverally aſunder, but joint together, hath not, ſay you, the death of <hi>John Reeve</hi> made void thy pretended Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to all intents, conſtructions and purpoſes whatſoever? Or if <hi>John Reeve</hi> and thy ſelf did pretend to be the two Witneſſes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. and to have power given to them? Hath not, ſaith he, the death of <hi>John Reeve</hi> made it evident againſt you to be none of them? and ſo he goeth on repeating moſt part of the 11 chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> as if it were to be fulfilled legally as it is ſet down in the Letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. M. Reply.</hi> That the death of <hi>John Reeve</hi> doth not make void my Commiſſion, no more then the death of <hi>Aaron</hi> did make void <hi>Moſes</hi> Commiſſion of the Law, neither was the Commiſſion of the Law made void when <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf was dead, or taken out of this world, but ſtood in full force and vertue after that that many hundred years, and was never made void until <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt and Chriſt did enter into the Miniſtery of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; for <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was the laſt Prophet of the Law, and in his death the Commiſſion of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was made void and of none effect to thoſe that did believe in Ieſus Chriſt, which brought in a better Covenant, or a better Commiſſion than that of the Law: ſo likewiſe the worſhip of the Goſpel of Jeſus which was ſet up by his Apoſtles, which was according to the faith which they had in Jeſus Chriſt his being the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of God, and Saviour of them that believed: but this Commiſſion of the Apoſtles did ſtand in full force and vertue
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62519:40"/>
but a matter of three hundred yeares, yet the Apoſtles which were the Commiſſioners, did not live themſelves above forty years after their Lord Chriſt was put to death, muſt that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion therefore be made void, becauſe the Commiſsioners were all dead? ſurely no. And this I further do affirm, that never ſince that three hundred years there hath not a man been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated from God, to be a Meſſenger, Miniſter, or Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of Chriſt, to preach the everlaſting Goſpel of life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, until that God ſpake to <hi>John Reeve</hi> in the year 1651. for all men that have exerciſed the Office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger, or Ambaſſador of Chriſt ſince that three hundred years to the year 1651. have run before they were ſent; for God ſent none of them by voice of words, but they have preached only from the letter of the Scriptures, or elſe from the light within, as the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> do, but have had no Commiſsion from Chriſt without them, though much good hath bin done by their preaching, and a great deal of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: but let that paſs, becauſe I have ſpoken of that more at large in <hi>the Interpretation of Rev. Chap.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>So I ſay though <hi>John Reeve</hi> be dead, and I were dead alſo, yet will not this Commiſsion of the Spirit be made void: for this I ſay, as long as there is faith and believers of this Commiſſion, it will not be void and loſe its vertue, which I know will be to the end of the world, though perhaps I my ſelf may be either put to to death, or die naturally within few years, yet the faith in this doctrine which we the Witneſſes of the Spirit have declared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the true God, his form &amp; nature before he became fleſh, and what he is now, and the form and nature of the right Devil before he became fleſh, and what he is now, with the place and nature of hell, and of heaven, the perſon and nature of Angels, and the mortality of the ſoul: Theſe ſix points of doctrine, with many more heavenly Secrets which hath been declared by Us, I ſay that there will be faith in ſome men and women to believe and underſtand theſe things which we have written, even to the worlds end, ſo that my Commiſsion will not be void, reverſed, and undone, though I were dead. Alſo I being the laſt true Prophet and Witneſs that ever ſhall come, which is more than any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or Prophet could ſay, therefore who ever ſhall truly believe theſe things, may be the more comforted and revived that redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption is ſo near at hand, when as all tears ſhall be wiped away
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62519:41"/>
from your eyes; and not onely ſo, but you ſhall enter into the joy of our good God and Savior in whom ye have believed, even the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who is both God and Man clothed with fleſh and bone, who poured out his ſould unto death, whoſe blood was no leſs then the blood of God, and this is that blood, that who ever can believe it, it will ſprinkle their ſouls here, and make them pure and clean, ſo that nothing ſhall offend or cauſe any fear of eternal death, but this natural death ſhall be but as a door of intrance into thoſe eternal joys, where we ſhall ſee our God face to face: and if you <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> had but read that book of mine of the Interpretation of <hi>Revel.</hi> chap. 10 you would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have repeated ſo much of it in your Pamphlet as you have, to prove me a falſe Witneſs; for there is every particular verſe in that chapter opened and expounded, beſides many other places in the <hi>Revelation</hi> opened, more then all the learned men in the world hath or could do, but it is a vain thing to talk of any hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſecrets to <hi>Quakers,</hi> for they will not beſtow a penny in any writings but their own, let them coſt ever ſo much pains the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and charge the printing, but if they can ſee them for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing perhaps they will view it a little ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtly over, but as to buy I hardly know any <hi>Quaker</hi> that doth, ſurely they are afraid they ſhould loſe their believers if they ſhould ſee my works: now I am very free that any believer of this Commiſſion ſhould ſee their writings, not fearing they will draw them away. God hath ſent a Commiſsion into the world to knock them down into that bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs-pit, where ſhall be weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth for evermore: and do you rage, and rail, and ſlight, and do what you can, you ſhall not be delivered from that ſentence and curſe which I have pronounced upon you, neither is the Doctrine of this Commiſſion any deceit, neither is it pride and preſumption in me, in what I have ſaid concerning you, but as true judgement as ever was paſt upon any man by any Prophet or Apoſtle, or by any true Judge of the Land, without envy or malice, but in true diſcerning and knowledge of the ſpiritual Law of the Scriptures, have I given Judgement upon you and others, whereunto I ſhall ſet my hand and ſeal, and if the Law can do it, ſeal it with my Blood.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Lodowick Muggleton.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62519:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
